<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Vindication of Her Grace, Mary Dutchess of Norfolk. Being a true account of the proceedings before the House of Lords, (from Jan. 7th. 1691. to Febr. 17th. following) upon His Grace the Duke of Norfolk's bill, entituled, An act to dissolve the marriage, &amp;c. occasioned, by several libellous pamphlets lately published, and dispersed, under the same pretence and title. / [Publis]hed by the direction of Her Grace the Dutchess of Norfolk.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10237</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80925048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80925048</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80925048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2900:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Vindication of Her Grace, Mary Dutchess of Norfolk. Being a true account of the proceedings before the House of Lords, (from Jan. 7th. 1691. to Febr. 17th. following) upon His Grace the Duke of Norfolk's bill, entituled, An act to dissolve the marriage, &amp;c. occasioned, by several libellous pamphlets lately published, and dispersed, under the same pretence and title. / [Publis]hed by the direction of Her Grace the Dutchess of Norfolk.</title>
                  <author>Norfolk, Mary Howard, Duchess of, 1659?-1705.</author>
                  <author>Norfolk, Henry Howard, Duke of, 1655-1701.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, stained and torn with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norfolk, Mary Howard, --  Duchess of, 1659?-1705.</term>
               <term>Norfolk, Henry Howard, --  Duke of, 1655-1701.</term>
               <term>Trials (Adultery) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trials (Divorce) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192144:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION Of her GRACE <hi>Mary Dutcheſs of Norfolk.</hi> Being a true Account of the PROCEEDINGS BEFORE THE Houſe of Lords, (From <hi>Jan.</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1691. to <hi>Febr.</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> following) Upon his GRACE The DUKE of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s BILL, ENTITULED, <hi>An Act to Diſſolve the MARRIAGE,</hi> &amp;c. OCCASIONED, By ſeveral Libellous PAMPHLETS lately Publiſhed, and Diſperſed, under the ſame Pretence and Title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by the Direction of her Grace the Dutcheſs of</hi> Norfolk,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second EDITION Corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:192144:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192144:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THere have been lately printed, and made publick, Two ſcandalous Pamphlets; the one under the Title of [<hi>The Proceedings before the Houſe of Lords, between the Duke and Dutcheſs of</hi> Norfolk:] The other is called [<hi>The farther Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Proceedings in the Houſe of Lords, in the Affair of the Duke and Dutcheſs of</hi> Norfolk; <hi>with the Bill of Divorce.</hi>] Now theſe Two Papers are ſo far from a faithful Narrative of the ſaid Proceedings, that what with confounding the Order of the Tranſaction, and diſguiſing the Truth of Things, by induſtrious Omiſſious, groſs Imperfections, and wilful Miſtakes. This pretended Account has made it abſolutely neceſſary, even for the ſake of common Juſtice, to ſet the World right in the Story: To which end the entire Series of this Affair is here ſet forth, from Point to Point, juſt as it paſſed before their Lordſhips, and ſtands upon their Journal; with ſuch Notes upon the Evidence on both ſides as the Nature of the Caſe requires, and as the reaſon of it will fairly bear.</p>
            <p>The Reader will obſerve here, upon this Relation, that the two Principal Witneſſes produced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> are <hi>Row. Owen</hi> and <hi>Marg. Elwood,</hi> for they Swear poſitively to the ſtreſs of the Queſtion, whereas all the reſt is but Circumſtantial and made uſe of only for Aggravation, Prejudice, and Clamour: So that upon invalidating their Teſtimony, the main Cauſe falls effectually to the Ground, ſaving only the unavoidable Misfortune of many an Innocent Perſon that ſuffers under the Impoſſibility of proving a Negative; there being no Pence againſt uncharitable Preſumptions. Now taking this for granted, (as it is not to be demed) the Reader is only deſired to lay ſeriouſly to Hear the Improbability of the Fact that is ſworn againſt the Dutcheſs, in ſome Caſes, and the utter Impoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of it to be true in others: The Tampering and Practice that has been uſed, the Inconſiſtency of the Witneſſes with themſelves, their Character, and Credit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (one of them, <hi>Ann Burton,</hi> being trapt in a falſe Oath, out of her own Mouth, upon the very place of Examination.)</p>
            <p>The Reader will alſo take notice, that of <hi>26 Witneſſes</hi> produced in Favour of the Duke, one half of them are <hi>Principals,</hi> and the other only <hi>Seconds. Peter Scriber, Andrew Anderſon, Robert Hemming, John Reynolds,</hi> and <hi>Margaret Foſter,</hi> are Five of the former Number; but ſpeaking little or nothing to the Merits of the Queſtion, it was not thought worth the while to offer Exceptions to their Teſtimony; though to the other Eight, that is to ſay, <hi>Owen, Elwood, Hudſon, Burton, Varelſt, Tho. Foſter, Lloyd</hi> and <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> there were ſeveral Witneſſes on the behalf of the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs to invalidate their Credit, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Two to the Firſt, Six to the Second, Two to the Third, Four to the Fourth, One to the Fifth, Two to the Sixth, Two to the Seventh, and Six to the laſt. It is very remarkable alſo, after all theſe Exceptions to every one of the Duke's principal Witneſſes, that the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Dutcheſſes Witneſſes paſſed current without any contradiction, ſaving only that <hi>Henry Dagley</hi> and <hi>John Hoskins</hi> were examined againſt the Credit of <hi>John Hall,</hi> in the Caſe of <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> (leaving four Witneſſes more in the ſame Caſe untouch'd;) and <hi>Edith Sawbridge,</hi> againſt the Teſtimony of Mrs. <hi>Judith Stourton,</hi> which Depoſitions the Reader will find to be of little or no moment, as to the matter in hand. This puts it paſt Diſpute, that they had nothing more to ſay againſt the Witneſſes for the Dutcheſs, but ſtopt at theſe Three for want of farther Pretence. The Reſult in ſhort is this, That all the material Witneſſes to the Charge are Impeached, and the Evidence on the other ſide ſtands <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntainted. To ſay nothing of the unanſwerable Reaſons that prevailed with
<pb facs="tcp:192144:3"/>the Lords finally to Reject the Bill, eſpecially conſidering the Solemnity of the Proceedings: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Cauſe was kept up on from the 7th. of <hi>January</hi> to the 17th. of <hi>February</hi> following. All the Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and about the Town being ſummon'd, by an Order of the Houſe bearing date <hi>Die Veneris Feb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1691.</hi> to attend at Twelve of the Clock on the <hi>Tueſday</hi> following. And the Officers that ſummone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them to give an Account of what Lords they ſummoned; purſuant to which Order their Lordſhips met according to the Appointment: and after ſome previous Debates, Adjourned till the next Day, when the Depoſitions on both ſides were read at the Table by the Clerk, as will be ſeen more at large upon the following Journal. And after a long and ſolemn Debate, The Queſtion being put, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Bill, intituled, An Act to Diſſolve the Marriage of</hi> Henry <hi>Duke of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>Ear Marſhal of</hi> England, <hi>with the Lady</hi> Mary Mordant, <hi>and to enable the ſaid Duke to Marry again, ſhall be read a ſecond time.</hi> It was reſolved in the Negative.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THis Account of the Proceedings before the Houſe of Lords by the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs, with her Defence, was deſign'd to have been Publiſhed ſoon after the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Cauſe in <hi>February, 1691.</hi> But that there might be no Offence given to the Duke, It was thought adviſable to ſuſpend it.</p>
            <p>But ſince that, albeit the Dutcheſs did take ſuch care not to give the Duke any manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Offence; yet he thought fit to bring his Action againſt Mr. <hi>Jermaine</hi> (in hopes of a new Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to proſecute the Dutcheſs) and did obtain a Verdict in the Court of King's Bench in <hi>November</hi> laſt, and a <hi>100</hi> Marks Damages: In which Action the Dutcheſs was no Party, nor could any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be made for her there.</p>
            <p>Now in this Cauſe, the Witneſſes produced by the Duke were the ſame that were examined before the Lords when the Bill was firſt Rejected, and the Dutcheſs Acquitted, and particularly <hi>Owen, Elwood, Burton,</hi> and <hi>Hudſon,</hi> who ſpake to Matters in <hi>1685.</hi> But the moſt Material of the Dutcheſſes Witneſſes, who could have confronted them, were not produced at the Tryal; becauſe thoſe Witneſſes of the Duke did ſpeak of things not in Iſſue, and therefore thoſe of the Dutcheſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere thought unneceſſary in that Cauſe, ſpeaking to things out of that time to which the Duke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad confin'd himſelf by his own Declaration: And though there were two or three new Witneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roduc'd by the Duke at the Tryal, yet nothing of Fact pretended to be was proved. And though it was impoſſible to ſpeak any thing to the Diſcredit of thoſe Witneſſes then, yet by Enquiry ſince<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they are found to be of no better Reputation than the firſt, (as in due time may appear.) And particularly as to <hi>Bowtell</hi> (to ſay no more at preſent) he ſtands upon the Journal of the Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Commons to have given an untrue Information againſt Captain <hi>Motley,</hi> and upon it was Or dered to be taken into Cuſtody, who afterwards petition'd to be diſcharg'd, and being brought t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Bar, and owni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g his Fault, had a Reprimand by the Speaker, and at length diſcharged paying his Fees.</p>
            <p>Now upon the Reputation of this Verdict, though the Dutcheſs was no Party, nor her Witneſſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined as aforeſaid, yet the Duke was pleaſed to offer a new Bill to the Lords the 22th of <hi>Decemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> laſt, for <hi>Diſſolving the Marriage,</hi> &amp;c. But the Dehate for Receiving or not Receiving it u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Adjourn'd to the 29th following, and from thence to the 31th, and from thence to the ſecond <hi>January,</hi> when after a long and ſerious Debate, The Bill was again Rejected: So that now it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not be thought Impertinent for this true Account to appear to the World.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192144:3"/>
            <head>A Vindication of her Grace MARY Dutcheſs of <hi>NORFOLK,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <p>THE 7th. of <hi>January</hi> the ſaid Bill was lodg'd in the Houſe of Lords.</p>
               <p>The 8th. of <hi>January</hi> the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> having received Intimation, that the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> was this Day offering a Bill to the Houſe of Lords, for Diſſolving the Marriage between them, and that the ſame was under De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> their Lordſhips; She was adviſed to preſent the following Petition.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled,</head>
                           <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                           <p>THat your Petitioner being informed, that the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> is at this time offering a Bill to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, for Diſſolving the Marriage between him and your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Your Petitioner Humbly prays ſhe may be heard by Your Lordſhips, before ſuch Bill be received. And Your Petitioner will ever pray, <hi>&amp;c. M. Norfolk.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which Petition their Lordſhips were pleaſed to make the following Order, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Vineris <hi>8</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>A Bill having been offered to this Houſe, on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> to diſſolve the Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid Duke and his Dutcheſs; It was ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, that Her Grace ſhall have notice thereof, and may be heard, by her Counſel, at the Bar of this Houſe, on <hi>Tueſday</hi> next at 12 of the Clock; what ſhe hath to object againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the ſaid Bill; at which time the ſaid Duke may alſo be heard by his Counſel, for the ſaid Bill, if he ſhall think fit.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parlimentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <head>Die Martis <hi>12</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter hearing Counſel this day, at the Bar, what they could object for her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the receiving of a Bill offered by his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> to diſſolve the Marriage between him and his Dutcheſs: As alſo the Counſel of his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> for receiving the ſaid Bill. And after Conſideration of what was offered by Counſel, on either ſide, and a long Debate thereupon:</p>
               <p>This Queſtion was put.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the Duke of</hi> Norfolk's <hi>Bill ſhould be received?</hi> It was Reſolved in the Affirmative.</p>
               <p>Which Bill is as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="bill">
                           <head>An Act to Diſſolve the Marriage of <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> with the Lady <hi>Mary Mordant,</hi> and to enable the ſaid Duke to Marry again.</head>
                           <p>FOraſmuch as <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> having been Married to the Lady <hi>Mary Mordant,</hi> hath made full proof that his ſaid Wife is guilty of, and hath committed Adultery on her part: And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> hath no Iſſue, nor can have any probable expectation of Poſterity to ſucceed him in his Honours, Dignities and Eſtate, unleſs the ſaid Marriage be declared void, by Authority of Parliament, and the ſaid Duke be enabled to Marry any other Woman. The King and Queens Moſt Excellent Majeſties, upon the Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition of the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Premiſes into their Royal Conſideration, for divers weighty Reaſons, are pleaſed that it be Enacted; And be it Enacted, by the King and Queens Moſt Excellent Majeſties, and by and with the Advice and Conſent of the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, That the ſaid Marriage between the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary</hi> his Wife, ſhall from henceforth be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192144:4"/>null and void; and is by Authority of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Declared, Adjudged, and Enacted to be null, and void, to all Intents, Conſtructions, and Purpoſes, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And that it ſhall and may be lawful to, and for the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> at any time, or times, hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to Contract Matrimony, and to Marry (as well in the Life-time of the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> as if ſhe were naturally dead) with any other Woman, or Women, with whom he might lawfully Marry, in caſe the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary</hi> was not living: And that ſuch Matrimony, when had and celebrated, ſhall be a good, juſt, and lawful Marriage, and ſo ſhall be adjudged, deemed and taken, to all Intents, Conſtructions, and Purpoſes. And that all and every Children, and Child; born in ſuch Matrimony, ſhall be deemed, adjudged and taken, to be born in lawful Wedlock, and to be Legitimate and Inheritable, and ſhall Inherit the ſaid Dukedom of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> Office of Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> and all other Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Dignities, Baronies, Honours, and Titles of Honour, Lands, Tenements, and other Hereditaments, from, and by, their Fathers, Mothers, and other Anceſtors, in like manner and form, as any other Child, or Children, born in lawful Matrimony, ſhall or may inherit, or be inheritable, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Courſe of Inheritances uſed in this Realm: And to have and enjoy all Privileges, Preheminencies, Benefits, Advantages, Claims and Demands, as any other Child, or Children, born in lawful Wedlock, may have, or claim, by the Laws or Cuſtoms of this Kingdom. And be it far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted, That the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſhall he Intituled to be Tenant, by Courteſie, of the Lands and Inheritance of ſuch Wife, whom he ſhall hereafter marry: And ſuch Wife as he ſhall ſo marry, ſhall be Intitled to a Dower of the Lands and Tenements of the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and of ſuch Eſtate whereof ſhe ſhall be Dowable, as any other Husband, or Wife, may, or might claim, have, or enjoy: And the Child, or Children, born in ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage ſhall, and may, derive and make Title, by Deſcent or otherwiſe, to, and from any their Anceſtors, as any other Child, or Children may do, any Law, Statute, Reſtraint, Prohibition, Ordinance, Canon, Conſtitution, Preſcription or Cuſtom, had, made, exerciſed, or uſed to the contrary of the Premiſſes, or any of them, in any wiſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. And be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary</hi> ſhall be, and is hereby barred and excluded of, and from all Dower and Thirds, and of, and from, all Right and Title of Dower, and Thirds, unto, or out of any the Honours, Mannors, Lands or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments of the ſaid Duke. And that all Conveyances, Join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Settlements, Limitations and Creations of Uſes and Truſts, of, into, or out of, any Honours, Mannors, Lands or Hereditaments, at any time heretofore made by the ſaid Duke, or any of his ſaid Anceſtors, or Truſtees, unto, or upon, or for the uſe or benefit of the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> or any the Iſſue of her Body, or for raiſing, diſcharging, or counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuring any the Mannors, Lands or Hereditaments of the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> or any of her Anceſtors, ſhall be from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth utterly void, and of none effect: And all and every the ſaid Honours, Mannors, Lands or Hereditaments of the ſaid Duke, or any of his Anceſtors, or Truſtees, ſhall from henceforth remain, and be to, and for, the uſe and benefit of the ſaid Duke, and ſuch other Perſon, or Perſons, and for ſuch Eſtates and Intereſts, and in ſuch manner and form, as if the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary</hi> was now naturally dead, without any Iſſue of her Body. And alſo, That all Limitations and Creations, of any Uſe, Eſtate, Power or Truſt, made by any of the Anceſtors of the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> unto, or for the uſe or benefit of the ſaid Duke, his Heirs or Aſſigns, out of any the Mannors, Lands or Hereditaments, of any of the Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the ſaid Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhall be from henceforth void and of none effect.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <head>13 <hi>Januarii,</hi> 1691.</head>
               <p>THE Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Bill aforeſaid, having been ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday received and read. The Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> preſented the following Petition to Their Lordſhips this Day.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in Parliament aſſembled,</head>
                           <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi>
                           </head>
                           <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                           <p>THat your Petitioner being Married to the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> fourteen Years and upwards, never had, or receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from her Husband, any Intimation of a Miſdemeanor, on her part, againſt him; which, joined to her Innocency of the Crime mentioned in the Bill, makes this Proceeding before your Lordſhips very ſurprizing to her: Her Perſon, Eſtate, and Honour, which is more dear to her than her Life, being now brought in queſtion.</p>
                           <p>Your Petitioner humbly prays ſhe may have a Copy of the particular Charge againſt her, with the Names of the Witneſſes, and reaſonable time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed her to anſwer the ſame, before any farther Proceedings upon the Bill.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Mary Norfolk.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which Petition the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>Die Mercurii <hi>13</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>UPon reading the Petition of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That Sir <hi>Richard Reynes,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Hedges,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Oxenden,</hi> do attend this Houſe to Morrow at ten of the Clock in the Forenoon.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <head>14 <hi>Januarii,</hi> 1691. After having heard the Civil Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, the following Order was made.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Jovis <hi>14</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>AFter hearing this day the Civil Lawyers, purſuant to the Order Yeſterday, upon reading the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Petition, It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſhall being in the Charge againſt his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192144:4"/>Dutcheſs, and particularly to the Perſon, Time and Place, by <hi>Saturday</hi> next, at twelve of the Clock.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <head>16 <hi>Januarii,</hi> 1691.</head>
               <p>This Day the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> brought in the following Charge againſt his Dutcheſs.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="charge">
                           <head>The Charge which <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Earl Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal of <hi>England,</hi> doth exhibit againſt his Wife <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> before the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, purſuant to their Lordſhips Order of the 14th. of <hi>January, 1691.</hi> is for the Crime of Adultery.</head>
                           <p>THE Perſon charg'd to commit the ſaid Crime with the ſaid Dutcheſs is <hi>John Jermaine,</hi> of the Pariſh of <hi>S. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet's,</hi> in the Liberty of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>The Times when the ſaid Crime was committed, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Months of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>December,</hi> 1685. and ſeveral times ſince.</p>
                           <p>The Places where the ſaid Crime was committed, are at <hi>Whitehall, Windſor,</hi> and within the Pariſhes of S. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> S. <hi>Martin</hi>'s in the Fields, S. <hi>James</hi>'s, S. <hi>Ann</hi>'s within the Liberty of <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> And in the Pariſh of <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and Marſhal.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Sabbati, <hi>16</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>UPon reading this Day the Charge which <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> hath exhibited againſt his Wife, <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> for the Crime of Adultery. It is Ordered, by the Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in Parliament aſſembled, That her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> do attend this Houſe on <hi>Monday</hi> next, or ſome Perſon on her behalf, then to receive a Copy of the Charge againſt her.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <head>19 <hi>Januarii,</hi> 1691.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="answer">
                           <head>The Anſwer of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> to the Charge exhibited againſt her by the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> before the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</head>
                           <p>THis Reſpondent is adviſed, that the Charge exhibited by the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> into this Honourable Houſe againſt her, as to Time and Place, is too general, and is not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant, nor doth anſwer the end of your Lordſhips Order of the 14th. inſtant, made upon the humble Petition of this Reſpondent. Wherefore ſhe doth humbly hope, and pray, your Lordſhips will not oblige her to make any further Anſwer, till the Duke ſhall bring in a particular, and certain Charge, as to Time, and Place, againſt her.</p>
                           <p>And this Reſpondent doth the rather humbly inſiſt, That your Lordſhips would pleaſe to require the Duke to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and certain, in theſe material Circumſtances of his Charge againſt her; for that it appears, by his own ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein, that the ſuppoſed Crimes objected to her, and alledged to be committed, were above ſix Years before the Bill was offered to this Honourable Houſe: during moſt of which time, at the advice, and by the approbation of the Duke, was, and continued beyond the Seas, to eaſe him in his Charge, and Part; He frequently declaring, that when he ſhould be more eaſie in his Fortune, they ſhould live together.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>M. Norfolk.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which Anſwer the following Order was made. And the Duke's Second Charge delivered in the ſame Day.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Martis, <hi>19</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>IT is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, That her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> ſhall have a Copy of the Duke's Charge delivered this day againſt her: And that ſhe, or Sir <hi>Thomas Pinfold,</hi> do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Houſe, to Morrow at 11 of the Clock in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, to anſwer to the ſaid Charge.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Which Copy is as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="charge">
                           <head>The Charge which <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> doth exhibit againſt his Wife <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> before the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, purſuant to Their Lordſhips Order of the 14th of <hi>January, 1691,</hi> is for the Crime of Adultery.</head>
                           <p>THE Perſon charged to commit the ſaid Crime with the ſaid Dutcheſs, is one <hi>John Jermaine,</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>The Times, and Places, when the ſaid Crime was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, were at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> in the Months of <hi>June, July, Auguſt,</hi> ſome, or one of them, in the Year 1685. At <hi>Windſer</hi> in the Months of <hi>July, Auguſt,</hi> or <hi>September,</hi> ſome, or one of them, in the ſaid Year 1685. In the Pariſh of St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter, March, April, May, June,</hi> ſome, or one of them, in the Year of our Lord 1690. And in the ſaid Pariſh of St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the Months of <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1690. In the Pariſh of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> in the Months of <hi>May, June, July, Auguſt;</hi> ſome, or one of them, in the Year 1691.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and Marſhal.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which, the next Day <hi>(viz.)</hi> the 20th of <hi>January,</hi> 1691, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> preſented the following Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192144:5"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in Parliament aſſembled,</head>
                           <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                           <p>THat your Petitioner was ſerved with an Order of this Honourable Houſe, late laſt Night, to attend your Lordſhips this Day, by Eleven of the Clock, either in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or by Sir <hi>Thomas Pinfold,</hi> to anſwer to a new Charge brought in againſt her, by her Husband the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Your Petitioner is adviſed, That, for her juſt Defence, it is neceſſary to alledge in her Anſwer ſeveral ſpecial Matters relating both to the Duke and her ſelf.</p>
                           <p>That in this ſhort time appointed by Your Lordſhips, your Petitioner finds it impoſſible to inſtruct Counſel, to prepare ſuch an Anſwer as ſhe is adviſed is neceſſary to put in.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore Your Petitioner Humbly prays Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, ſhe may have convenient time to put in her Anſwer to the ſaid Charge.</p>
                           <p>And Your Petitioner will ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>M. Norfolk.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Mercurii <hi>20</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>UPon reading the Petition of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> praying that She may have convenient time for anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Charge put in againſt her, by his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Yeſterday. It is Ordered by the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſhall peremptorily anſwer, by her Self, or Proctor, to the ſaid Charge, to Morrow at Eleven of the Clock in the Forenoon.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Accordingly, <hi>January</hi> the 21ſt.</p>
               <p>The Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> delivered in the following Anſwer.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="answer">
                           <p>I <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> under Proteſtation, That the pretended Charge of Adultery given againſt me, in the Honourable Houſe of Peers, was, and is, general, inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and ſuch as, I humbly conceive, I am not bound by Law to give anſwer unto. Yet knowing my own Innocency, and that I am not guilty of the pretended Crime, this Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation being Sacred to me, I ſhall, and do, under the Matters and Qualifications hereafter mentioned, anſwer, and ſay, hereby affirming, That having been marryed to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> for near 15 Years, he never did (till this pretended Charge given againſt me) in the leaſt pretend, or intimate, unto me, that I had ever injured his Bed; but did always treat me with great Kindneſs and Reſpect. And about the Year 1685, at his requeſt, and deſire, I did go with him from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> and there continued with him for ſome time; where his Grace, being under an Indiſpoſition and continuing ſo for ſome time, He ſhewed ſuch Affection to me, and put ſo great Truſt and Confidence in me, that all ſuch things that were adminiſtred to him, in order to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, He did not, nor would receive any of them but what came from my Hands; and I did with great care attend him: And being recovered, He told me his Occaſions requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to go for <hi>England,</hi> but he would return to me in <hi>France</hi> within ſome ſhort time, and bring Me home to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and at his parting with Me, he ſhewed great Affection to Me, and in great Paſſion of Love, with Tears in his Eyes, ſaid, He had Ten Thouſand Pardons to ask Me, deſiring my Patience, and that I ſhould return into <hi>England</hi> to him in ſome ſhort time. And after his Grace's return into <hi>England,</hi> he having notice from me, that my Lodgings was inconvenient, and deſiring his leave to change the ſame, He wrote me word very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ffectionately, that God forbid he ſhould conſtrain me to any Inconveniency, and left me to my Liberty therein. And before his parting with me, in <hi>France,</hi> as a Teſtimony of his Love and Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ction to me, He ordered 400 <abbr>
                                 <hi>l.</hi>
                              </abbr> yearly to be paid unto me, out of his own Eſtate, by Quarterly Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, over and above the ſeparate Maintenance ſettled upon me, by my Father, upon my Marriage with him. And that after his Arrival in <hi>England,</hi> he made ſeveral Viſits to my Mother, the Counteſs of <hi>Peterborow;</hi> and with great Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, and Reſpect, ask'd her Bleſſing, and told her, he had left me well, and ſafe, in <hi>France;</hi> and ſaid, that his own Debts were preſſing upon him; but if her Daughter (mean my Self) would conſent that the Mannor of <hi>Drayton,</hi> and other places, ſhould be ſettled upon him, and his Heirs, he ſhould thereby be made a happy Man. And I coming into <hi>England,</hi> his Grace having put off Houſe-keeping, and dwelling in the Counteſs of <hi>Peterborow</hi>'s Lodgings, in St. <hi>James</hi>'s, for about 2 Years; and I ſuing him for Alimony (the ſaid 400 <abbr>
                                 <hi>l.</hi>
                              </abbr> a Year not being paid unto me) He did not, during that Suit, object any Crime againſt me, which had been proper for him to have done, to avoid Alimony, if I had been guilty. And I, the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> being at <hi>Drayton</hi> in <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> his Grace did write very affectionately to me. And that Diſturbances happening in thoſe parts, in <hi>Nov.</hi> 1688, I left <hi>Drayton;</hi> and, with the conſent of the Duke, went beyond Seas, and there continued till ſent for by my Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then returned; which was in or about <hi>Octob.</hi> 1691. with the Duke's conſent. And then Applications being made to me by the Duke my Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>band, to join with him in the Sale of <hi>Caſtle-Riſing,</hi> and other Eſtates: But I being adviſed this muſt be injurious to me, could not joyn therein, which I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly apprehend to be the true Cauſe and Occaſion of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt my Honour, on the Duke my Husband's part.</p>
                           <p>And I the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> adhering to my Proteſtation of my Innocency, and denying that I am guilty of the pretended Crime charged againſt me, and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to Impeach my Husband of any Crime whatſoever; yet being adviſed, That, by the Laws of the Land, a Husband ſuing a Divorce for the Adultery of his Wife, he ought not to obtain any Sentence of Divorce, if he be proved Guilty of the ſame.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192144:5"/>
Wherefore this Reſpondent doth aver, and is ready to prove, that the Duke her Husband was, and is guilty of Adultery, and hath continued in the Courſe of Adultery for theſe ten Years laſt paſt, and doth ſo continue.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>My Lords.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>IT is my Misfortune to be thus accuſed; I had rather ſtand charch'd for High-Treaſon before your Lordſhips, than with this ignominious Crime. In the Charge for High-Treaſon, the manner of Tryals, and the ways of Proceedings, are known; ſo is the Puniſhment in this Caſe againſt me.</p>
                           <p>Your Lordſhips are now creating new ways of Proceeding againſt me, and a new Law to puniſh me; and this for a Crime ſuppos'd, and alledg'd to be committed ſeven Years paſt, in another Reign, after publick Indemnities in the Seſſions of Parliaments, many Sittings of Parliaments, and Diſſolutions of others, without mentioning this Crime againſt me. My Counſels are to ſeek how to adviſe my Defence in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, being altogether ſtrange, and without Preſident, or Example.</p>
                           <p>I find my Proſecution now to be very violent, and my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to be very ſwift upon me, having had but one Night to prepare my Anſwer to this general Charge. I do in this Place publickly declare, I am innocent of what is objected to me, and am not guilty of defiling my Husband's Bed: I am not guilty of the Crime charg'd againſt me. I hope (being thus accuſed) I may, without Vanity and Vain-Glory, ſay, what is well known, That I am not only the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Wife, but alſo born and deſcended from Parents and Anceſtors of the Ancient Nobility; That your Lordſhip's Anceſtors, and my Anceſtors, who ſat in this Houſe, knew no ſuch Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: It is with regret that I bring this Anſwer for my Self, and againſt my Husband; but it being my Defence, I hope you will excuſe me.</p>
                           <p>And if your Lordſhips ſhall, in your great Wiſdom, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed farther in this matter, I hope, and do moſt heartily pray, that I may hereafter have convenient time to make my Proofs, and full Defence; and then I doubt not of your Lordſhip's Juſtice to me, as well as for my Husband, who Sits and Votes with your Lordſhips.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>M. Norfolk.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon the delivering the ſaid Anſwer, the next Day the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Veneris, <hi>22</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>IT is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, That His Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſhall produce his Witneſſes, to Morrow at Ten of the Clock in the Forenoon to be ſworn. And that her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> do attend this Houſe, by her ſelf, or Proctor, at the ſame time; and may have Orders for Witneſſes if ſhe pleaſes.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Accordingly, 23 <hi>Januarii,</hi> 1691, the Duke's Witneſſes were produced; and whoſe Names are as followeth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret Ellwood</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ann Burton</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rowland Owen</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Hudſon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Simon Varelſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peter Scriber</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Reynolds</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Lloyd</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Andrew Anderſon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret Foſter</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary Boyle</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rice Jones</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ann Jones</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Hoskins</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Hall</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary Hall</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Barly</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Wood</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Owen</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Dagley</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Miles</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Colvin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>After theſe ſeveral Witneſſes were produc'd, on behalf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and had given in their ſeveral Places <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Aboad, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The following Oath was adminiſtred to them.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ſhall true Anſwer make to all ſuch Queſtions as ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> be asked you by this Honourable Houſe, in relation to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Charge of Adultery, brought in by the Duke of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Dutcheſs of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>with</hi> John Germaine; <hi>you ſhall declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> your whole Knowledge of this Matter, and ſhall ſpeak the Truth the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth, as well upon the matter you ſhall be examined on behalf of his Grace the Duke of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>as upon ſuch Interrogatories as ſhall be exhibited on behalf of the Dutcheſs of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>without Favour or Affection to either Party.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So help you God, and by the Contents of this Book.</p>
               </q>
               <p>After the Oath adminiſtred, as aforeſaid, the following O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Sabbati, <hi>23</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>IT is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, That the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Proctor ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap> have a Copy of what was taken upon Swearing the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi>'s Witneſſes at the Bar; and that the Duke's Witneſſes ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> give in their Evidence at the Bar, on <hi>Tueſday</hi> next, at Ten of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> Clock in the Forenoon: and that the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> her ſelf, Proctor and Council, ſhall attend, together with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Duke's Proctor and Council, at the ſame time.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliament</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>After Examination of Witneſſes on behalf of the Duke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Martis, <hi>26</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>AFter hearing this day, the Witneſſes on the behalf of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> it is Ordered by the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That <hi>Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                    <desc>•••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> next, at Ten of the Clock in the Forenoon, ſhall be, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> hereby appointed, for her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> make her Defence, by her Proctor, or Council; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Council and Proctor be then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> ſent, and the Witneſſes who this day delivered their Eviden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> or Oaths, on his Grace's behalf: And that the Dutcheſs ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> have an Order for ſuch Witneſſes, as ſhe ſhall think fit to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> uſe of, on her Grace's behalf.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliament</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192144:6"/>
Upon which Order, the Dutcheſs was adviſed to preſent the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollowing Petition.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled.</head>
                           <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                           <p>THat ſince the Examination of Witneſſes before your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, againſt your Petitioner, upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> laſt, the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Endeavour and Diligence hath been uſed, to prepare for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>er Defence againſt the time appointed by your Lordſhips.</p>
                           <p>That your Petitioner is very much concerned, that, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ceſſary Defence of her ſelf, ſhe ſhould be forced to lie under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>he Charge ſworn againſt her, one moment beyond the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iven her by your Lordſhips.</p>
                           <p>But, upon a Conſultation with her Council and Sollicitor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ſt Night, ſhe is adviſed, that it is abſolutely neceſſary for her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Addreſs to your Lordſhips for Time, till <hi>Monday</hi> next, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ring in her Defence, ſome of her moſt material Witneſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>g remote from <hi>London;</hi> and though ſhe has ſent for them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſed all means poſſible to get them ready by the time appointed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> cannot be able to have them here before <hi>Monday</hi> next.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore Your Petitioner humbly prays your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips (it being a Caſe of the higheſt Concern, and utmoſt Importance, to your Petitioner) to give her Time, till <hi>Monday</hi> next, to bring in her Defence.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c. M. Norfolk.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Upon which Petition, the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Veneris, <hi>29</hi> Januarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>WHereas this Day was appointed for her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Forfolk</hi> to make her Defence; upon reading the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> praying (it being a Caſe of the higheſt Concern, and utmoſt Importance to her) to give her time, till <hi>Monday</hi> next, to bring in her Defence; after hearing her Council at the Bar, and upon Oath made, that ſome of the Dutcheſs's material Witneſſes are out of Town, It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> hath hereby Time given her for making her Defence, until <hi>Monday</hi> the Firſt Day of <hi>February</hi> next, at Eleven of the Clock in the Forenoon.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Accordingly, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> began her Defence: And the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Lunae, <hi>1.</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>IT is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, That on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> next, at Eleven of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ock in the Forenoon, the Houſe ſhall proceed in hearing the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Evidence; and that all the Witneſſes that have been ſworn on either Side, do then attend the Houſe.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Which they did; and the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Mercurii, <hi>3</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>AFter having this Day heard ſeveral Witneſſes on behalf of her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> as alſo for his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parliament aſſembled, That her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Council ſhall proceed in her Grace's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, on <hi>Saturday</hi> next, at Twelve of the Clock.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>They proceeded accordingly; and the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Sabbati, <hi>6</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>AFter having this Day heard ſeveral Witneſſes on the behalf of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That the Council for his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſhall proceed to examine Witneſſes on <hi>Tueſday</hi> next, at Twelve of the Clock.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Which accordingly they did; and the following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Martis, <hi>9</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>AFter hearing ſome Witneſſes this Day, on the behalf of his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parliament aſſembled, That the Council for his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> as alſo the Council for her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> ſhall be heard on <hi>Thurſday</hi> next, at Twelve of the Clock, to ſum up the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on either ſide; and that Mrs. <hi>Sawbridge</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Stour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> do then attend, to be heard.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Council attended accordingly, but not heard; and their Lordſhips were pleaſed to make the following Order.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Jovis, <hi>11</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>IT is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, That the Council for his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> as alſo the Council for her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> ſhall be heard to Morrow, at One of the Clock in the Afternoon, to ſum up the Evidence on either ſide; and that Mrs. <hi>Sawbridge</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Stourton</hi> do then attend to be heard.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:192144:6"/>
After Evidence ſummed up, this following Order was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="order">
                           <head>Die Veneris, <hi>12</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>AFter hearing this Day the Counſel, and a Civilian, for his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> and alſo Counſel, and a Civil Lawyer, for her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up the Evidence for their Graces ſeverally, It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parliament aſſembled, That on <hi>Tueſday</hi> next, at Twelve of the Clock, this Houſe ſhall proceed on the debate of this Buſineſs; and that then no other Buſineſs whatſoever ſhall intervene: And that all the Lords in and about the Town ſhall be ſummonned then to attend; and that the Officers that ſummon them give the Houſe an account of what Lords they ſummon</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Matter was accordingly entred upon; and after ſome previous Debates by their Lordſhips, they were pleaſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ till the next Day, when they proceeded, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <head>Die Mercurii, <hi>17</hi> Februarii, <hi>1691.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Depoſitions taken at ſeveral Times before, on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his Grace the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> as alſo thoſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on the behalf of her Grace the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> were read at the Table, by the Clerk.</p>
               <p>After long Debate thereon, The Queſtion was put.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the Bill Entituled,</hi> An Act to Diſſolve the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> with the Lady <hi>Mary Mordant,</hi> and to enable the ſaid Duke to Marry again, <hi>Shall be Read a Second Time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was Reſolved in the Negative,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="proceedings">
            <head>The <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>LORDS</hi> upon the <hi>Evidence.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Rowland Owen</hi> Examined on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ROwland Owen</hi> ſaith that Mr. <hi>Keyner,</hi> about Six Years ſince, being the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Butler, ordered him to carry the things out; the Lodgings being open, he ſaw Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> in Bed with the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> the Dutcheſs leap'd out of the Bed, and put on a Morning Gown, and <hi>Germaine</hi> hid himſelf in Bed; this was between five and ſix a Clock in the Evening, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Fortnight before <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Day; he did not tell the Duke: he is ſure it was <hi>Germaine;</hi> he ſaw him often, twice or thrice a day; the outward door of the Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigs was ſhut, but he opened it with a Key he had,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rowland Owen</hi> examined a ſecond time, ſaith he never ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Key of the Lodgings but once, that Mr. <hi>Keymer</hi> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him the Key, when he went as (as he told him) to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Blew Poſts in the <hi>Haymarket,</hi> to beſpeak the Dutcheſs's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; he ſaith he ſaw not <hi>Francis Knight</hi> then in the Lodgings nor any other Woman but the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> he ſaith h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> hath ſeen <hi>Keymer</hi> often open the outward Door of the Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, when he hath been by, without calling <hi>Francis Knight</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he ſaith that he himſelf opened the firſt Door with the Key; the Second Door was not cloſe ſhut, and the third Door was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen: he ſaith two of the Doors are ſtreight forward, and the third turns a little on the right Hand; he ſaith he was gon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in at the third Door when the Dutcheſs leapt out of Bed.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes produced to the Credit of <hi>Rowland Owen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDward Silveſter</hi> ſaith he hath known <hi>Rowland Owen</hi> three or four Years, and he hath truſted him in Buſineſs, and he hath ever been very faithful; he hath truſted him in Stores to the King, and he might have imbezell'd, but ever found him honeſt; and he hath had three or four Thouſand Pounds worth of Goods that he might have imbezell'd, and hath had opportunities of doing ill things, but never did: he hath truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with every thing he hath; he hath had more than 20 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> imbezell'd by others, but he never imbezell'd a half penny: H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> knows not well who recommended him to him; he hath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hundred Men now, and he knows not that three of them wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> recommended: He hath truſted him with Goods an hundre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and an hunded times that he might have imbezell'd; and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that he hath ſo truſted have cozened him, and he hath l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 20 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> in a Months time by them; He works at our wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and that better than twenty that he hath had, and he's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Porter; he ſaith he knows not Mr. <hi>Negus,</hi> nor was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quainted with him till Yeſterday.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Jones</hi> ſaith he hath known <hi>Rowland Owen</hi> above th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Years, and that he's a very honeſt Man, and that he ever for him faithful; that he lodged in his Houſe, and that he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> have done him injuries if he would, and he hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ployed elſe where, and he never heard ill of him; he beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> he's a Man of a better Principle than to take a falſe Oath</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Cooke</hi> ſaith that he hath known <hi>Rowland O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> five Years, and knows not but that he's an honeſt Man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaith that he maintains his Family by his Labour; he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 01 Neighbour, and never heard him taxed with any Miſdemean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes Sworn on behalf of the Dutcheſs, for inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dating the Teſtimony of <hi>Rowland Owen. (v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRancis Knight</hi> ſaith ſhe knows <hi>Rowland Owen,</hi> as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Fellow-Servant in the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Houſe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hath known him a Year, he was running Porter, to carry Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and Wood; he was not truſted with any Keys; ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> truſted with the Keys to the Lodgings, and ſhe always k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Key to the outward Door to the Lodgings, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> no other Key; and ſhe never delivered it to any Body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſometimes left it with the Lady <hi>Peterborough</hi>'s Houſe-ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe never let this <hi>Owen</hi> have that Key, or any other Key t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192144:7"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odgings, it was below her to do it; he never went into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ner Rooms, no farther than the Steps to the Outward Room; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e's a pityful beggerly Fellow; he laid the Stewar'ds Cloath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd had no other Livelyhood; ſhe lived with my Lady ſix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ars and upwards, and all the while had the Key to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Door; ſhe ſaith you muſt firſt come into the Room cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed the Footmens waiting Room, then into the Dining Room, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen into the Bed-Chamber; the Doors are ſideways: ſhe made the Dutcheſs's Bed conſtantly; ſhe lock'd the Door, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ept the Key in her pocket; ſhe had the Key of the Rooms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill the Counteſs of <hi>Weſtmoreland</hi> had the Lodgings, which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill the Duke and Dutcheſs left them, which was ten or twelve days before <hi>Bartholomewtide,</hi> ſix Years ago,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry Kemer</hi> ſaith that he knew <hi>Rowland Owen</hi> Street-Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er; he ſaith that he (this witneſs) could never get into the Lodgings, but when he had the Key from <hi>Francis Knight;</hi> he ſaith <hi>Owen</hi> never came into the Lodgings, but had a Key to a Houſe where the empty Bottles were, which was without the Lodgings; and he himſelf could not get into the Lodgings but by <hi>Frances Knight;</hi> he never had the Key in his own Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſion; he never ſaw <hi>Owen</hi> farther than the Paſſage-Room; he ſaith that the Doors are not oppoſite to one another; he ſaith <hi>Francis Knight</hi> never gave him the Key; he always found her there to open the Doors, or in the Room; he never had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny Key that would open the Lodgings: <hi>Owen</hi> never told him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat he caught the Dutcheſs in the manner as is ſaid; he knows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot of any Livelyhood he had, beſide laying the Steward's Cloath: <hi>Owen</hi> had Wages from the Duke, and lodg'd at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke's Houſe in St. <hi>James</hi>'s; he ſent Bottles, Pewter-Plates, Forks and Spoons, Bread, and Linnen ſometimes by him, from the Duke's Houſe to the Lodgings in <hi>White-hall:</hi> When he was not there to receive them himſelf, he gave him directions to deliver them to <hi>Francis Knight,</hi> or gave him the Key of the Cupboard. Being ask'd whether he hath ever gone by another Name than <hi>Keymer,</hi> de deſired to be excuſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to anſwer; he refuſed alſo to anſwer whether he had known any Lady go by the name of <hi>Bateman:</hi> Afterwards he ſaid he did know one to do ſo; he ſaith ſhe went by the Name of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> he ſaith it was the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> that went by the Name of <hi>Bateman,</hi> and ſhe went ſo he believes for a Year; it was at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> but he knows not at whoſe Houſe there; he never ſaw <hi>Germaine</hi> there; it was a Year, or half a Year ſince, he knows not certainly; the Houſe is called by the Name of <hi>Scriber</hi>'s Houſe, a Dyer; he never ſaw Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> at <hi>Scriber</hi>'s with the Lady <hi>Bate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> he ſaith he himſelf went by the Name of <hi>Goodman</hi> when he lived with this Lady <hi>Bateman;</hi> he ſaith that he knows not that <hi>Germaine</hi> was ever at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> by that name or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he ſaith he never paid any Rent for the Houſe at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> nor knows that <hi>Germaine</hi> paid any for it; but he ſaith he was a Servant to the Dutcheſs at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> but knows not what Office he was in, but ſhe paid him his Wages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry Keymer,</hi> examined to what <hi>Rowland Owen</hi> ſaid at his ſecond Examination, ſaith he never gave him the Key of the Lodgings, and ſaith he never had the Key of the Lodgings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er in the firſt place to conſider, and compare the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on both ſides Secondly, to examine the Credit of the Witneſſes, Thirdly. The reaſonable Probability of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Sworn, according to the common Courſe and Practice of the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Owen</hi> Swears' That being ſent by <hi>Henry Keymer,</hi> the Duke's Butler, to carry the things out, and the Lodgings being open, he ſaw Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> and the Dutcheſs in Bed; and to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the Story, he ſays that two of the Doors are ſtreight for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, giving to underſtand that the Doors being open and one aginſt another, a body may ſee the Bed out of the firſt Room intot the hird; that <hi>Keymer</hi> gave him the Key of the outward Door and upon the unlocking of it he made this Diſcovery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Frances Knight</hi> encounters this Evidence with a Depoſition, that ſhe kept the Key of the outward Door, her ſelf, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it to no body, but now and then to my Lady <hi>Peterbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi>'s Houſe-keeper: That <hi>Owen</hi> never went into any of the Inner Rooms, and that the Doors are ſideways.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry Keymer</hi> ſaith alſo, that he himſelf could not get into the Lodgings, but by <hi>Frances Knight;</hi> that he never gave <hi>Owen</hi> the Key; nor ever had it in his Poſſeſſion; that he never ſaw <hi>Owen</hi> beyond the Paſſage-Room; nay that <hi>Frances Knight</hi> never gave him the Key, but that he ſtill went to her to open the Door, and that he never had any Key to the Lodgings; that whenever he ſent <hi>Owen</hi> with Plates, Spoons, and the like, from Duke's Houſe to the Lodgings in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> he was either there himſelf to receive them, or directed <hi>Owen</hi> to deliver them to <hi>Francis Knight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if theſe two Witneſſs ſpeak Truth, <hi>Owen</hi> was never in the inner Rooms at all; he never had the Key of the outward Door, and the Doors are not ſtreight forward as <hi>Owen</hi> Swears they are, which is a Matter of Fact eaſily cleared.</p>
                  <p>As to the Credit of <hi>Rowland Owen, Edward Silveſter, John Jones,</hi> and <hi>Edward Cook</hi> are produced in his Favour. The firſt ſwears he never knew him ſteal or cozen, as if the caſe were Pilfery. The ſecond that <hi>Owen</hi> might have done him wrong, and did not, and thence infers that he would not take a Falſe Oath. The third, that he knows nothing to the contrary of his being an honeſt Man. So that here are three Surmiſes for the Reputation of <hi>Owen,</hi> which are juſt nothing to the purpoſe, on the one hand: and two point blank Proofs, upon Oath, againſt him on the other; and not one Syllable all this while to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage the Teſtimony of either <hi>Knight</hi> or <hi>Keymer;</hi> though there are ſeveral pinching Paſſages in the Evidence, that, if they were falſe, might be detected by Hundreds of Witneſſes. And for an Inſtance of <hi>Keymer</hi>'s Tenderneſs of an Oath, he has own'd ſome things, upon the cloſe of his Examination, to the ſeeming Prejudice of the Dutcheſs her ſelf. This is meant of their going by borrowed Names: but as things ſtood at that time with many Perſons of Honour, under her Grace's Circumſtance, it was no Scandal to conceal either their Names or their Aboads. But as to the true Reaſon of the Dutcheſs's Retirement and living in a manner ſo <hi>Incognito;</hi> The Earl of <hi>Peterborow</hi> falling deſperately ſick in the <hi>Tower,</hi> her Grace came over upon it, from beyond the Seas, to be within diſtance in caſe the Sickneſs ſhould have proved Mortal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Dutcheſs had at that time nothing to live upon, but an Exhibition from her Father, and one half of that was made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver too for the Payment of her Debts; ſo that not being in condition to appear anſwerable to her Quality, ſhe thought
<pb facs="tcp:192144:7"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> honour, Prudence and Juſtice to retrench her Expences, which ſhe could not better do than by ſuch a Retreat.</p>
                  <p>It is in the next place to be obſerved, how <hi>Owen</hi> interferes with himſelf; the Lodgings, he ſays, being open, he ſaw Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> in Bed with the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> the Dutcheſs leap'd out of the Bed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This muſt naturally be underſtood upon the opening of the firſt Door; and, to the end it ſhould be taken ſo, he ſays, that the two firſt doors were ſtreight forward, and that the third turns a little. Now if ſo, how could he ſee the Bed out of the firſt Room into the third? And then he forgets himſelf again, in ſaying that the ſecond door was not cloſe ſhut, and the third open; ſo that he has now doubled the difficulty: there was no ſeeing into the Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, both becauſe the ſecond door was almoſt cloſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the third was ſideways. It is to be noted alſo, that the Bed ſtands quite out of ſight of the Bed chamber door, which is ſufficient of it ſelf alone to overthrow <hi>Owen</hi>'s Teſtimony. But upon ſecond thoughts, he takes himſelf tripping, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of mending the Matter makes it worſe; it comes into his Head by this time, that there was no ſeeing them in Bed out of the firſt Room, and ſo thinks to help it out with a Flam at the wrong End of his Information, that indeed he was in at the third door when the Dutcheſs leap'd out of her Bed. Now to take the Tale his own way, can any Body imagine that <hi>Owen</hi> ſhould unlock the outward door, lay down his Lumber, paſs theſe two Rooms into the third, the Dutcheſs and Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> both awake too, and all this Noiſe not give them the Alarm?</p>
                  <p>To come now to the Probability of the thing, <hi>Keymer</hi> gave him the Key, he ſays, only for once it ſeems, for he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had it either before or ſince. Has not this the Face now of a Contrivance calculated for a particular turn? Is it not highly improbable again, that a pitiful drudging Fellow that earn'd his Bread, by doing Porters work for the Family, ſhould have the Dutcheſs's Bed-chamber laid open to him? And ſo for the Morning-Gown, and <hi>Germaine</hi>'s hiding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Bed, had they no other Cloaths or Garments lying by them, that <hi>Owen</hi> ſhould have the luck to ſee juſt this and nothing elſe. But his Leſſon was to ſwear <hi>Nudus cum Nuda,</hi> and <hi>Solus cum Sola,</hi> to bring the Proofs up to the ſtraitneſs of the Law, and that was the part he had to play. Or, to take the Caſe yet another way. If <hi>Owen</hi> had ſeen them out of the firſt Room, can any Body think he would have ventur'd after that into the Bed-chamber? Or, if he did not ſee them in the firſt Room, what had he to do in the other Room at all? But over and above all the reſt, for an Amour of this Quality, to be carryed on thus in the Face of the Sun, the doors and the Curtains open; let any Man ask his own Conſcience if he does not look upon it as an Impoſture, without a Preſident from the Creation to this day.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Margaret Ellwood</hi> Examined on the Behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArgaret Ellwood</hi> ſaith ſhe had a Company to ſee the Lodgings at <hi>Windſor,</hi> in the Firſt Year of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, about three or four of the Clock in the Afternoon; a Woman told her that my Lady was not there, but ſhe opening the door ſaw my Lady upon the Stools in an ill poſture; Mr. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi>'s Britches were down; he pull'd them up, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hand on his Sword, ſaying, <hi>God Dam you for a Whore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have you the impudence to come here?</hi> My Lady bid him ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> me down. He ſcattered ſome Concerns. that is, Man's Natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> on the Boards: She ſaw no Nakedneſs but her Knee, or a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> above. Another time after ſhe found <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Handk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> chief and Ruffles in my Lady's Bed; my Lady's Woman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there was <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Name upon them. Another time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaw Mr. <hi>Cornwal</hi> let Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> out of my Lady's Cloſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> She ſaw <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Legs within hers when ſhe came the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> time into the Room, and his Breeches were about his Heel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> The firſt time was in <hi>Bartholomew-Fair</hi> time. Mrs. <hi>Knifet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> told her it was <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Linnen.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes produced to the Credit of <hi>Marg. Ellwood.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>CAptain <hi>Charles Potts</hi> ſaith, he hath known <hi>Margaret Ell<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wood</hi> ſix or ſeven Years, and that ſhe was Servant to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and that ſhe behaved her ſelf well and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently there; her Husband was a Soldier in his Company, and was, as he hath heard, a Shoomaker.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Faucet</hi> ſaith, He knew <hi>Margaret Ellwood,</hi> while ſhe was the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Servant about two or three Years: He never heard any Scandal or Diſgrace of the Woman, but that ſhe carried her ſelf civilly: He knows not whether ſhe kept an Ale-houſe in <hi>Windſor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lawrence Parnell</hi> ſaith, he knows <hi>Margaret Ellwood;</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lived in his Houſe in <hi>Brook-Market,</hi> next <hi>Eaſter</hi> will be tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Years: He knows nothing amiſs of her; ſhe took care f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> her Living; he never knew her keep ill Hours; ſhe took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Room in his Houſe, ſome of the Rent is behind, he thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thirty two Shillings, her Husband and the Woman gave hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Bond for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes Sworn on the behalf of the Dutcheſs, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> invalidating the Teſtimony of <hi>Margaret Ellwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MIchael Haddon</hi> ſaith, he hath been acquainted with <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garet Ellwood</hi> four, five, ſix or ſeven Years. When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> firſt knew her, her Husband was a Soldier in the Duke's Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany, and ſhe was, as he hath heard, an Under Houſe-keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> He believes ſhe was turned out of the Duke's Service. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwards ſhe ſold Drink in a Houſe of his at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> away in his Debt by Night, without paying him; ſhe took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Goods with her; this was in 1689.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joyce Heath</hi> ſaith, ſhe knows <hi>Margaret Ellwood;</hi> ſhe liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in a Cellar of hers, and in a back Houſe of hers, but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſame time, three Quarters of a Year in <hi>Brook-Market,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout <hi>Michaelmas</hi> loſt; ſhe paid the Landlady but Eleve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Shillings Six Pence. Her Courſe of Life was not good; ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> was in an inferiour Condition; her Husband was a Cobler in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Stall, and ſhe had five Children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Tervis</hi> ſaith, ſhe hath but a ſlender Acquaintance with <hi>Margaret Ellwood;</hi> but the ſaid <hi>Ellwood</hi> ſent to borrow a Scarf of her the <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> laſt, and ſaith, that going the next Day for her Scarf, ſhe the ſaid <hi>Ellwood</hi> deſired it for a longer time, for it might be 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> in her way, for ſhe was
<pb facs="tcp:192144:8"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Witneſs for the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who was to be divorc'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m his Dutcheſs; and that the Duke ſent his Chariot for her. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>old her, there could be no Separation in Marriage, except <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ultery could be proved: And that I could not think it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>able to believe, that ſo mean a Servant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſhe could be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ectator to ſo ill an Action as that was. She ſaid, ſhe thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e could do the Duke no Kindneſs in going; for ſhe never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w other harm by the Dutcheſs, than that ſhe ſaw Gentlemen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome to and fro to the Houſe: But the Duke had ſent for her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ſhe muſt go.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Jones</hi> ſaith, She knows <hi>Margaret Ellwood;</hi> who ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eard ſay, the Lady Dutcheſs ſent for her a little before <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs</hi> laſt, and ſaid, <hi>Margaret,</hi> I deſire you to ſpeak the truth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> would not have you diſoblige my Lord in the leaſt. <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Ellwood</hi> ſaid, ſhe never knew no harm by her Grace. The Dutcheſs demanded the Keys of her, and ſhe gave them her; and the Dutcheſs gave them to her the ſaid <hi>Ellwood</hi> again, the next Morning. The diſcourſe was a few days before <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs</hi> laſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ann Roſs</hi> ſaith, She knows <hi>Margaret Ellwood;</hi> who came to her Houſe, and told her, about two Months ſince, that the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſent for her to witneſs; for there would be a Divorce between the Duke and Dutcheſs: And I asking her what ſhe could ſay? She anſwered, ſhe could ſay but little, but that ſhe knew no ill by the Dutcheſs; but that ſhe was a good generous ſpirited Lady, and ſhe never knew any ill Action by her in her Life. I bid her have a care what ſhe went about, for that would do the Duke but little kindneſs. The Dutcheſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſaid, called for the Keys of her Lodgings, but gave her them back next Morning. She ſaith, That laſt Week ſhe went to her to demand a Debt; and ſhe promiſed to come and pay it her: She ſaith, ſhe went to the Porter, at the Duke's, to ask for her; but the Porter ſaid, ſhe was not within; but meeting with her Child there, ſhe ſaid, ſhe was within; and brought her, the Witneſs, to her, in the Duke's Houſe; and ſhe made her very welcom, and ſent her Husband with her, the Witneſs, to ſee her Children's Lodging, in the <hi>Green-Meuſe,</hi> near the Duke's Houſe. She ſaith, <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s Husband told her, upon asking how the Cauſe went, that his Wife was to have 30 <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> ſetled on her, and to go to <hi>Windſor</hi> to live, and to have the ſhewing the Caſtle. She ſaith, that upon her going to ſee the Children, and commending their Lodgings, that <hi>Ell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi>'s Maid, or Woman, told her, they paid 4 <abbr>
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </abbr> a Week for their Lodging She ſaith, the Children were well cloathed, with good Frocks and Top knots, and they uſed to be ragged; and that her Husband uſed to allow her but ſix Pence a day for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r and her Children. She ſaith, that <hi>Margaret Ellwood</hi> told her, ſhe had been with the Dutcheſs; and that her Grace bid her do nothing to diſoblige her Lord, but ſpeak the Truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Roſs</hi> ſaith, She knows <hi>Margaret Ellwood:</hi> She ſaith, ſhe heard <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s Husband ſay, that the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> had taken care of his Wife and Children, and ſetled 30 <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> on them, and her Habitation was to be at <hi>Windſor-Caſtle;</hi> and ſaid, that my Lord Duke would be divorced, for he was to have a great Fortune of Twenty Thouſand Pounds a Year. This Diſcourſe was the laſt Week, and her Father was preſent, and her Mother was juſt gone out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>Here is a foul and a ſuſpicious. Story in this Depoſition of <hi>Margaret Ellwood,</hi> wherein ſhe ſtands ſingly upon the Credit of her own Teſtimony, without any Colour, or Corroborating Evidence to ſupport it: Only Captain <hi>Charles Potts, John Faucet,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Parnell,</hi> are produced to ſpeak to her perſonal Reputation. The firſt ſays, ſhe behaved her ſelf well and prudently in the Duke's Houſe; the Second and Third, that they knew no ill by her.</p>
                  <p>There were produced on the behalf of the Dutcheſs, and to invalidate the Teſtimony of <hi>Margaret Ellwood,</hi> theſe ſix Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <hi>Michael Haddon, Joyce Heath, Mary Trevis, Mary Jones, Ann Roſs,</hi> and <hi>Mary Roſs. Mary Trevis, Mary Jones,</hi> and <hi>Ann Roſs,</hi> do all depoſe, that about <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> laſt, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Dutcheſs and Mr. <hi>Germaine, Margaret Ellwood</hi> told each of theſe Witneſſes reſpectively, that ſhe never ſaw or knew any thing of ill by the ſaid Dutcheſs; and yet <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bears date in the firſt Year of King <hi>James. Mary Trevis</hi> ſwears farther, that upon the next <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> laſt, <hi>Ellwood</hi> told her, upon borrowing a Scarf of her, that it might be 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> in her way; for the Duke was to be divorced from his Dutcheſs, and he had ſent his Chariot for her, and ſhe was to be a Witneſs. <hi>Ann Roſs</hi> ſpeaks alſo to the ſame effect, how <hi>Ellwood</hi> told her there would be a Divorce, and the Duke had ſent for her to be a Witneſs: And likewiſe ſaith, that <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s Husband told her, that his Wife was to have 30 <hi>
                        <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> ſetled upon her, and live at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and have the ſhewing of the Caſtle. <hi>Mary Roſs</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe alſo, with the Witneſs above, as to what <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s Husband ſaid of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> the Settlement, and the Divorce; adding alſo, that the Duke was to have a great Fortune, (according to the common Rumour then about the Town:) <hi>Mary Roſs</hi>'s Father was by, and heard all this: It was about a Week before the date of this Information, that this Diſcourſe had paſſed.</p>
                  <p>Nay, the Dutcheſs was ſo clear in the matter, that ſhe ſent for <hi>Ellwood</hi> a little before <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> laſt, and bid her ſpeak the truth; as <hi>Ellwood</hi> her ſelf owned to <hi>Mary Jones</hi> and <hi>Ann Roſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To come now to the Quality and Credit of <hi>Margaret Ell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood. Haddon</hi> ſays, ſhe was his Tenant to an Ale-houſe in <hi>Windſor,</hi> in 1689, carry'd off her Goods by Night, and went away in his Debt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heath</hi> ſaith, ſhe lived in a Cellar, led an ill Courſe of Life, her Husband was a Cobler in a Stall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ann Roſs</hi> ſays, that ſhe had five Children, and that ſhe had but Six Pence a Day Maintenance for her ſelf and them.</p>
                  <p>This was her Condition till near <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> laſt, when all on a ſudden, as <hi>Ann Roſs</hi> depoſes, ſhe was taken into the Duke's Houſe, the Children new cloathed, and trickt up with good Frocks and Top knots, (which were, till then, all in Rags;) Lodgings provided for them at Four Shillings a Week, and a Maid to look to them; and no viſible means of doing all this. But, in fine, the Change was not wrought by Miracle, and leans much toward the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcourſe before-mentioned, that <hi>Ann</hi> and <hi>Mary Roſs</hi> had with <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s Husband.</p>
                  <p>The Queſtion, at laſt, is briefly this: Whether is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, a Woman under ſo many ſcandalous Circumſtances, and one that ſwears for her ſelf too; or ſix Witneſſes againſt her of ſo unqueſtionable Probity, that not ſo much as one of them could be impeached by the other Party?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:192144:8"/>
To paſs now to the palpable unlikelyhood of the Story barely in it ſelf: <hi>Ellwood</hi> was carrying Company, ſhe ſays, to ſee the Lodgings at <hi>Windſor;</hi> and opening the Door, ſhe ſaw and heard, as in her Depoſition. How came it now, that none of this Company ſhould be produc'd, or ſo much as nam'd, to ſecond <hi>Ellwood?</hi> For 'tis to be preſum'd, they muſt needs hear and ſee what paſs'd upon this Adventure, as much as ſhe her ſelf did; or if ſhe had but nam'd the Woman, who, ſhe ſays, told her my Lady was not there, it might have ſerv'd as a Collateral Inducement, for the giving of ſome ſort of Credit to it. But in a Matter of this Importance, to have ſo many Witneſſes within reach of being found out, and none to appear, looks very ill on their part, that were ſo much concern'd to produce them: And ſo for <hi>Germain</hi>'s threatning her, and the Dutcheſs's bidding him kick her down; no People in their right Wits, but would have try'd to ſtop her Mouth with fair Words, and a good Bribe, in ſuch a Caſe as this, rather than provoke her by Menaces and ill Language, to run open Mouth to the Duke with the Story, in Revenge, when ſhe had the Dutcheſs's Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Eſtate ſo abſolutely at her Mercy.</p>
                  <p>As to the buſineſs of Mr. <hi>Germain</hi>'s Handkerchief and Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, and his being let out of the Cloſet, the Contrivance is all of the ſame piece with the reſt; for why were not the Perſons nam'd in her Depoſition, produc'd to prove the Particulars therein mention'd, as well as <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s? It is moſt certain, that the Proſecutors could eaſily have done it, and that it was properly their Buſineſs and Intereſt ſo to do; for what ſignifies <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s ſingle Teſtimony, under her Circumſtances, without Corroborating Proofs? She tells us a Tale, of Company to ſee the Lodgings, a Woman that told her ſo and ſo, and another Woman and a Gentleman that ſaid and did this and that; and yet not one Creature at laſt to ſecond her Depoſition, nor any pretence of an Exception to the Evidence on the other ſide.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thomas Hudſon</hi> Examined, on behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas Hudſon</hi> ſaith, That the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> being at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> he was Butler at <hi>Windſor,</hi> when <hi>Germaine,</hi> and the Dutcheſs, and <hi>Cornwall</hi> went to play; <hi>Germaine</hi> ſent his Footman for clean Linnen, which he brought the next Morning. Mrs. <hi>Gwin</hi> ſaid to the Dutcheſs, The Dog would have lain with me; but ſhe would not lay the Dog where the Deer laid, for ſhe knew the Lady Dutcheſs would accept of him; after that, he ſaw a Shirt and Waſtcoat in the Cloſet, which my Lady's Woman and <hi>Ann Burton</hi> took away. My Lord being abſent we murmured among our ſelves, that my Lord was wrong'd. I told my Lord: Whereupon my Maſter <hi>Cragg</hi> had me to my Lord <hi>Peterborough</hi>'s Lodging, and threaten'd me, that he would prefer me to his Brother <hi>Richards,</hi> who turn'd me off in <hi>Germany.</hi> This was, as he thinks, in <hi>December</hi> or <hi>September,</hi> 1685. Mrs. <hi>Gwin</hi> ſpoke this in the <hi>Green Room;</hi> and he was in a Cloſet hard by, and the Door open, and ſo heard it.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſs ſworn on the behalf of the Dutcheſs, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validating the Teſtimony of <hi>Thomas Hudſon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WIlliam Purchaſe</hi> ſaith, That he knows <hi>Thomas Hudſon;</hi> who, he ſays, was never Butler to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> either at <hi>Windſor,</hi> or any other place: He, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was Under-Butler himſelf; <hi>Keymer</hi> was Butler <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and the Witneſs was Under Butler. He ſaith, <hi>Hudſon</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> on the Gentleman of the Horſe, and the Steward; he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Duke's Servant, nor waited at the Table, that he know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he was never ſuffer'd to come into the Room when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> or Dutcheſs was at Play. He ſaith, He, the Witneſs, was at <hi>Windſor</hi> at the time when the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> was at <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> but he was ſent to <hi>Drayton,</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was then the Duke's Servant, as Under-Butler; he knows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> where <hi>Keymer</hi> was; he ſaith he is now Servant to the Lord <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terborough.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Col. <hi>Jacob Richards</hi> ſaith, That he knows <hi>Thomas Hudſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> he was his Servant; he was recommended to him by Mr. <hi>Crag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> he was his Footman; he believes he was in his Service fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Months; he parted with him, becauſe he found him a tricki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Fellow: He told him, his Brother <hi>Cragg</hi> was to be kill'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> one <hi>Curry,</hi> and another Iriſhman: He, the Witneſs, writ to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Brother <hi>Cragg,</hi> and he advis'd the Witneſs to part with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for he did not think him fit to be truſted in his Travels; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon he paid him his Wages, and gave him Money to bear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Charges to <hi>England,</hi> and ſent a Trunk by him. One Mr. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> travell'd with the Witneſs; and his Father who then a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> now lives with the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> writ to us, That he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not think it fit for us to keep ſuch a Servant, for he was a dang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fellow, or to that effect. <hi>Hudſon</hi> never own'd any thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the Adultery to the Witneſs, but poſitively declar'd to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> he knew nothing of it: This was in <hi>January,</hi> 1685. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaith, that <hi>Cragg</hi> writ him Word, That <hi>Hudſon</hi> muſt needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Tricking Knave. He negligently told the Witneſs this of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Adultery; Curioſity made him ask it of him; for he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the Duke and Dutcheſs, and it was natural for him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Witneſs, to ask ſuch a Queſtion. He ſaith, he believes <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſaw ſome of his Letters: He ſaith, there were Printed Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> in the Trunk he ſent, but nothing of any conſiderable va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> He ſaith, <hi>Hudſon</hi> never cheated him of any thing that he k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> of; he hath truſted him with a 100 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> at a time: The T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> was deliver'd in <hi>England,</hi> and he believes he knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was in it: He ſaith, that asking <hi>Hudſon</hi> whether he knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thing of the Adultery charg'd on the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> Hudſon</hi> ſaid, he knew nothing of it: He, the Witneſs told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that it was ſaid, that it was he that had betray'd the Dutc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> He ſaid it was a falſe Accuſation, for he knew nothing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dſon</hi> ſwears himſelf the Duke's Butler at <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap> William Purchaſe</hi> ſwears that <hi>Hudſon</hi> was never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Duke's Butler.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hudſon</hi> ſays, that they went to Play, and that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heard Mrs. <hi>Gwin</hi> out of a Cloſet, ſaying as in the Evid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Mrs. <hi>Gwin</hi> is a dead Witneſs, and <hi>Hudſon</hi> but a Cloſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is little better. Now <hi>Purchaſe</hi> ſays again, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Hudſon</hi> was never ſuffer'd to come into the Room where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Duke or Dutcheſs was at Play.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hudſon</hi> ſays likewiſe, That the Servants murmured amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> themſelves, That my Lord was wrong'd, and that he told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lord of it. Colonel <hi>Jacob Richards</hi> depoſes, That he him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:192144:9"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng of a Noiſe of the Adultery; <hi>Hudſon</hi> made Anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it was a falſe Accuſation, and he knew nothing of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow as to <hi>Hudſon</hi>'s Credit, he was Colonel <hi>Richard</hi>'s Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>; who turn'd him off, as a Tricking Fellow, and not fit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e truſted. Mr. <hi>Negus,</hi> the Duke's Servant, both then and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, was of the ſame Opinion too; and adviſed, by Letter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> putting of him away, as a dangerous Fellow.</p>
                  <p>This Story, of Mr. <hi>Germain</hi>'s ſending his Man for clean Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> over Night, and the bringing it next Morning, has little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t, even ſuppoſing the Fact to be true. Firſt, The Order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is given bare-fac'd, and conſequently no Myſtery in it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ndly, There was a Set Company at Play, and that was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> opportunity for a Love-Intreague. Thirdly, it is no new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng for People to Sit-up all Night at Play, and change their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nnen next Morning, without any offence to Honeſty, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ood Manners, where they may have a Privacy ſo to do it. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> my Lady's Woman, and <hi>Ann Burton,</hi> took away the Shirt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d Waſtcoat, as he ſays they did, there's no great hurt in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>either; tho' it's much to have Three ſuch Confidents to ſuch Secret, an Under-Footman privy to the Intreague of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ain</hi>'s Man going and coming, and raking in the Womens Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, among the Linnen.</p>
                  <p>But ſtill the only proper Witneſſes are kept behind the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n. <hi>Ann Burton</hi> indeed is produced, and we ſhall ſee what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd of Evidence ſhe proves her ſelf in the next place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nn Burton</hi> Examin'd, on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANN B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RTON</hi> ſaith, ſhe was a Servant to the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk.</hi> When the Duke was gone to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> ſhe was at <hi>Windſor</hi> when my Lady went to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> with <hi>Germaine.</hi> When my Lady came home, after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſhe was in great haſte to go to bed; when ſhe was undreſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſaid ſhe would lock us out, becauſe ſhe would not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd before Eleven a Clock the next Morning, tho' the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Queen ſhould come. <hi>Hudſon</hi> told her <hi>Germaine</hi> was ſtill in the Houſe; whereupon we laid Chairs on the Back-Stairs, that we might hear him if he came down; the Chairs were not removed the next Morning: When <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Man came with his Linnen, he ſaid his Maſter was there. My Lady order'd a Fire to be made in my Lord's Room; where when ſhe was come, Mrs. <hi>Nelly Gwin</hi> came in, and ask'd her how ſhe lik'd her Night's Reſt? And being ask'd for <hi>Germaine,</hi> ſhe ſaid ſhe knew nothing of him. My Lady complaining of her Hair being out of order, <hi>Nelly</hi> anſwer'd, It was a hot Night with her, enough to put her Hair out of Powder and Curl too. Quickly after <hi>Cornwall</hi> came in and asked for <hi>Germaine;</hi> and my Lady ſaying ſhe knew nothing of him, <hi>Nelly Gwin</hi> ſaid, I queſtion not but he will come out by and by like a drownded Rat. With that, while I was cleaning the Dining Room, Mrs. <hi>Knifton</hi> called me, and ſhewed me in a Cloſet <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Shirt and Waſtcoat; and afterwards making my Lady's Bed, ſaw there were Two Prints where Two had laid. The Shirt and Waſtcoat were ſent by the Duke to the Lord <hi>Peterborough;</hi> ſhe ſaith ſhe is a ſingle Woman, and was never married. This was about <hi>Bartholomewtide</hi> Six Years ſince; ſhe ſuppoſeth the Bed was Stain'd both by a Man and a Woman.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes Sworn on the behalf of the Dutcheſs for the invalidating the Teſtimony of <hi>Ann Burton.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ANn Burton</hi> againſt her ſelf; upon ſeeing ſeveral Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes comes in, to prove her to be a Married Woman, (tho' ſhe had ſworn the contrary) was call'd to the Bar of the Lords, and there ſaith, ſhe was not Married when ſhe was at <hi>Windſor,</hi> ſince that ſhe hath been Married. <hi>Ann Burton</hi> was her Maiden Name, her Husband's Name was <hi>Benskin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Suſan Wheat-Croft</hi> ſaith, that ſhe knows <hi>Ann Burton,</hi> and that ſhe Lodged in her Houſe Sixteen Weeks, with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Robert Benskin,</hi> and ſhe ſaid ſhe ſhould have a parcel of Mony to be a Witneſs for the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> againſt his Dutcheſs; this was about <hi>March</hi> two Years ſince; her Husband ſaid he ſhould have a Commiſſion from the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and he ſhould have a great deal more from him, for his Wife is to be a material Witneſs againſt his Dutcheſs. They did nor pay her, the Witneſs, when they went away, nor ſince, they owed her Seven Pounds Fifteen Shillings; ſhe hath been ſeeking after them, and could not find them; ſhe left a Trunk with Rags in it, and went away privately, carrying away her Good's by Parcels.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Sheriff</hi> ſaith, that ſhe lives next Door to <hi>Warwick-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> and hath kept Houſe there near Seven Years, and hath known <hi>Ann Burton</hi> two Years; ſhe lived with my Lord <hi>Clare;</hi> while ſhe was there a Soldier, courted her; they uſed to come every day for a Fortnight or three Weeks to her Houſe to drink; ſhe ow'd her about 3 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> ſhe hath told her ſeveral times ſince, that ſhe was to be a Witneſs, for the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> againſt his Ducheſs, and ſhe was to have Mony for ſpeaking: She heard Mrs. <hi>Tod</hi> bid her always keep in a Story, and ſhe would do well. She, the Witneſs heard them talk of 30 or 40 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> Mrs. <hi>Burton</hi> ſhould get by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Witneſs; ſhe is not paid the 3 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> nor knows not whether ſhe ſhall be paid; but laſt Winter ſhe found her in <hi>Henrietta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> and ſhe deſired her, the Witneſs, not to take notice of her Name, nor what ſhe ſaid to her, for ſhe, the Witneſs, ſhould have her Mony in a ſhort time, when the Tryal was over; ſhe told her the ſame a little before that, when ſhe lived at Major <hi>Wildman</hi>'s; ſhe takes it to be in this Winter was Twelve month; ſhe thinks it was the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Tryal; ſhe, the Witneſs, keeps a Coffee-houſe, called <hi>Joe</hi>'s Coffee Houſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Purchaſe</hi> ſaith, that he knows <hi>Ann Burton;</hi> ſhe declared to him about a Year and a half after the Dutcheſs was charged with lying with <hi>Germaine,</hi> that ſhe knew nothing of it, and that the Dutcheſs was wrong'd as much as ever any Woman was, and that ſhe hoped to ſee thoſe puniſhed that were the Cauſe of the Accuſation: He ſaith, he went to ſee her as a Fellow-Servant, and he was not ſent by any one; and going to drink together, they fell into this Diſcourſe: He hath talk'd of this matter ſeveral Times (particularly to Mr. <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi>) ſince this Buſineſs was ſpoken of, having heard ſhe was to be a Witneſs againſt the Dutcheſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192144:9"/>
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ANN Burton</hi> has the Story over again of the Shirt and Waſtcoat, and of Mrs. <hi>Gwyn</hi>'s Diſcourſe, to which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough is ſaid already, and more needs not be ſaid upon the Evidence of a Perſon ſo manifeſtly forſworn. In her firſt Oath, ſhe ſwears her ſelf a ſingle Woman, and that ſhe was never married; but upon Witneſſes appearing to prove the contrary, ſhe was called to the Bar again, and own'd her ſelf to be Married, and that her Husbands Name was <hi>Benskin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Ann Burton</hi> had been a Lodger ſixteen Weeks to <hi>Suſan Wheatcroft,</hi> as appears by <hi>Wheatcroft</hi>'s Depoſition; ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed her Goods privately out of the Houſe by Parcels, and ſlipt away ſeven pound fifteen Shillings in her Debt; ſhe told <hi>Wheatcroft</hi> that ſhe was to be a Witneſs againſt the Dutcheſs, and that ſhe ſhould have Money; her Husband ſaying alſo, that his Wife was to be a material Witneſs againſt the Dutcheſs, and he himſelf ſhould have a Commiſſion, and more than that too.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Sheriff</hi> ſays, that preſſing <hi>Ann Burton</hi> for three Pound ſhe owed her; her Anſwer was, that ſhe was to be a Witneſs for the Duke againſt the Dutcheſs, and that in a ſhort time ſhe ſhould have Money, and then ſhe would pay her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Purchaſe</hi> ſwears, that about a Year and half after the Report concerning the Dutcheſs and Mr. <hi>Germaine, Ann Burton</hi> told him, the Dutcheſs was wrong'd, and ſhe hoped to ſee her Accuſers puniſhed: and that he himſelf hath often ſpoke of this paſſage to ſeveral, and particularly to Mr. <hi>Welborne.</hi> Take notice, that theſe Depoſitions for the Dutcheſs, as well as the former, have paſſed without any contradiction: That <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Man is neither produced, nor named; the Linnen (if any) brought as openly as it was ſent for. No Mrs. <hi>Knifton</hi> appears, and the whole Depoſition reſts upon the credit of a forſworn Woman.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Simon Varelſt</hi> examined on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SImon Varelſt</hi> ſaith, that he was at <hi>Windſor,</hi> to draw the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Picture, about ſix Years ſince, and had the Duke's Cloſet to put the Pictures in; when he had done and had been at home two or three days, <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> came to him much concern'd, and ſaid, you can do the Dutcheſs an extraordinary kindneſs, and you will oblige the Lord and Lady <hi>Peterborow</hi> in the higheſt degree; then he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me a Letter of the Dutcheſs to me, and read it to me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he told me there was a Shirt and Waſtcoat, and they are known to be his; he ſaid, I deſire you to ſave the Dutcheſs's Honour, I deſire that you will be ſo much a Gentleman as to own them to be yours, and that you left them there; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I was much concern'd there ſhould be ſuch a trouble, but I deſired to be excuſed, I could not do it without prejudice. He told me, the Lord and Lady <hi>Peterborow</hi> had diſcourſed the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> upon it, and if it were but my Linnen, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcourſe had wrought ſo much upon him, that if there came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny Evidence to aſſiſt him, he would leave off the purſuit; I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efuſed ſtill, he offered me a Purſe of Gold, and told me I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould make my Fortune by it; but I refuſing, Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vent away very much diſcontented; my Wife being in the next Room, overheard the diſcourſe between <hi>Germaine</hi> and me, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> told it, and ſpoke of it, or elſe I had not been here now.</p>
               <div type="testimony">
                  <head>
                     <hi>John Rothmell,</hi> Sworn a Witneſs on the behalf of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> for Invalidating the Teſtimony of <hi>Simon Varelſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JOhn Rothmell</hi> ſaith, that he lives in <hi>Crown Court</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> and is a <hi>Taylor:</hi> He ſaith, he knows <hi>Simon Varelst,</hi> and that he, the Witneſs, marry'd his half Siſter; he ſaith, that about a quarter of a year after the buſineſs of the Dutcheſs happen'd at <hi>Windſor,</hi> he was at <hi>Varelſt</hi>'s Houſe about eleven of the clock in the night, and <hi>Varelſt</hi> lock'd the Door, and told him, he had diſparag'd him by marrying his Siſter, and ſaid he would be his Death; and drew his Sword, and commanded him to ſtrip, that he might ſlaſh him at pleaſure; and the ſaid Witneſs did ſtrip for fear of his Life, knowing his Frenzy; and he ſtruck the Witneſs above a dozen times with his Sword, and threatned ſtill to have his Life, if he, the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did not fetch his Wife down that night, which was about Twelve a Clock, and which was about Six Weeks after ſhe lay in; and he was to bring her to be Whipt, and to bring ſix Rods with him; upon his, the Witneſſes Promiſe to do this, he let him go, and he hath not ſeen him ſince, but in the ſtreet. He had half a year before that been diſtracted for ſix weeks, and he, the Witneſs, fetch'd Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi> to him once, and the Doctor came ſeveral times afterwards to him. One night in that Sickneſs, he got from the Woman that watch'd him, and run about two hours in his Shirt and Waſtcoat, in a froſty night, and cut his Feer, and was brought home by the Watch; he ſaith, his, the Witneſs's Wife, was to have been here this day, as a Witneſs, and was here, but not having an hour to reckon, and being ill, is gone home with her Midwife: He ſaith, he never durſt go near <hi>Varelſt</hi> ſince he abus'd him. He ſaith, that Mrs. <hi>Varelſt,</hi> after ſhe came from <hi>Windſor,</hi> ſaid, that the Dutcheſs had ill people about her, and that ſhe believ'd her to be much wrong'd, and ſaid, ſhe could clear her about the ſcandal of the Linnen that was found; for whether it was or was not Mr. <hi>Varelſt</hi>'s Linnen, ſhe could do it; and ſaid, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing I had brought my Husbands Linnen down to be waſh'd, and the Landreſs fetching of it, ſhe might take it up, and leave ſome of it behind.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations on the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>THere needs no more to the overthrowing of <hi>Varelſt</hi>'s Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whatever it is, than the Teſtimony of <hi>John Roth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell,</hi> to prove him <hi>Non Compos;</hi> witneſs his Outrage upon <hi>Rothmell,</hi> the fantaſtical freak of ſending at Midnight for ſix Rods to whip his Siſter-in law; and another fit, for a matter of ſix weeks, when Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi> made him ſeveral Viſits to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him, his Frenzy being ſo violent upon him, that he broke looſe from his Keepers in a froſty night, and ran up and down the ſtreets in his Shirt, till he was taken up by the Watch: This is the ſum of <hi>Rothmell</hi>'s Teſtimony, and not one word op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd either to the Credit of the Witneſs, or the truth of the Depoſitions. But it may not be amiſs, after all this, yet to ſpeak a few words to the likelihood of what <hi>Varelſt</hi> has here depos'd.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> came to him, he ſays, with a Letter from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192144:10"/>Dutcheſs, which he read to him, and in the name of the Lord and Lady <hi>Peterborow,</hi> deſir'd him to ſay, the Shirt and Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat were his: but not one word all this while of the Contents of the Dutcheſſes Letter. He ſays again, that the Shirt and Waſtcoat were known to be his; now if they were known to be Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s, what good could <hi>Varelſt</hi> do by taking the matter upon himſelf; when he ſaw fair words would not do, there was a Purſe of Gold offer'd him, and that would not work neither. The Dutcheſs and Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> were wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully alter'd, ſure, in this caſe, from what they were in the buſineſs of <hi>Owen</hi> and <hi>Ellwood;</hi> there was no Purſe of Gold, or Dutcheſſes Letter to ſmother the matter; but on the contrary, <hi>Ellwood</hi> was threaten'd, provok'd, and defy'd, inſtead of cajoling her. And what was all this for at laſt, but only to remove a Jealouſie, and moſt ridiculouſly, at the ſame time, to condemn themſelves by a Confeſſion out of their own Mouths, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Suſpicion into a Certainty: Can any body imagine that they would not have done more to have ſuppreſt <hi>Owen</hi>'s and <hi>Ellwood</hi>'s evidence, than <hi>Ann Burton</hi>'s, or <hi>Simon Varelſt</hi>'s; who ſwears farther, that his Wife heard all this diſcourſe betwixt <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> and himſelf in the next Room, and told of it. Why was ſhe not produced then, or the perſons to whom ſhe told it? But <hi>Rothmell</hi> ſwears, that Mrs. <hi>Varelſt</hi> ſaid, the Dutcheſs had ill people about her, and was much wrong'd, and that ſhe herſelf could clear her about the ſcandal of the Linnen; ſo that 'tis plain, Mrs. <hi>Varelſt</hi> was not an Evidence for the preſent Turn.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi> Examined on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas Foſter</hi> ſaith, that he was Coach-man to Mr. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> and carried the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> often, about two years ſince in his Coach, and brought her home, and the Foot-men have had four Half-Crowns given them; and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> a <hi>Dutch-man,</hi> his helper, called it <hi>Huſh-Money;</hi> it was by right, againſt a Light, that he ſaw her Face in the Coach; it was about Seven or Eight a Clock at Night about this time a hear; he hath ſeen her Face once in the day time, ſhe looking out of a Saſh-Window, two Stories high, in Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Park-ſtreet;</hi> he knows her Face well enough; he hath ſeen her before, and ſince ſhe was Married.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes Sworn on the behalf of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> for Invalidating the Teſtimony of <hi>Thomas Foſter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JOhn Hall</hi> ſaith, that he lives at the <hi>Coffin</hi> in <hi>Tuttle-ſtreet,</hi> and is a Joiner; he ſaith, he hath known <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi> two years; and that about three weeks ſince, they being drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, and talking about the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> he ſaid, Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> had done ill things by him, in turning him off in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in turning him off here, and he was reſolv'd to be reveng'd of him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoſea Grimſley</hi> ſaith, he lives with Mr. <hi>Germaine,</hi> and that he hath known <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi> above a year and three months, in Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Service; he heard him ſay, in the laſt week of <hi>December</hi> laſt, in Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Houſe, about three days before he was turn'd away, that he thought it no more ſin to Murther his Maſter, than it was to kill a Louſe; he ſaith, he hath lived with Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> about a year and half; and that he never ſaw the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> with him; and that he hath ever ſince he came to him, lived with him in the place where he now lives; he ſaith, he never ſaw Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> with a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that was called the Lady <hi>Bateman,</hi> nor knows any ſuch Name or Perſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>THere is not one word in <hi>Foſter</hi>'s Evidence, true or falſe, that's worth the hearing, only it is levelled upon the main, at the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and Mr. <hi>Germaine;</hi> and <hi>John Hall</hi> gives the reaſon of it; for this ſame <hi>Foſter,</hi> he ſays, was Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Coach man, who he ſaid, would turn him off, and he would be revenged of him. <hi>Hoſea Grimſly</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies alſo, that ſome three days before <hi>Foſter</hi> was turned away, he ſaid, he thought it no more ſin to kill his Maſter, than to kill a Louſe. So, that the Evidence he gives, was grounded on the malice he bore his Maſter, for turning him off.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thomas Lloyd</hi> Examined on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THomas Lloyd</hi> ſaith, he knows one that went by the Name of the Lady <hi>Bateman,</hi> at her Houſe at <hi>Fox-hall;</hi> one <hi>Germaine,</hi> a Wine-Merchant, took the Houſe, ſhe came thither about Midſummer, 1689. She was off and on there till laſt Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. He hath ſeen the Perſon that went by the Name of the Lady <hi>Bateman;</hi> and it is the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk. Goodman</hi> was her chief Man, and his real name is <hi>Keymer.</hi> Her Brother, as was pretended, which he hath heard was Mr. <hi>Germaine,</hi> was the chief man that came there, ſometimes he came once or twice a Week, ſometimes oftner; he's certain, as the Servants ſaid, it was Captain <hi>Germaine</hi> that came there, every body ſaid it was he: He knows him not by his Name, but by Hear-ſay; if he could ſee him now he could tell whether it was he; he hath not ſeen him ſince the Lady went away; he believes <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> was there every month in both the laſt Summers; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay that <hi>Goodman</hi> was ever there, when <hi>Germaine</hi> was there he ſaw him ſeveral times there in <hi>May, June, July,</hi> and <hi>August,</hi> 1691. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s own Hair was then pretty long: He cannot poſitively ſwear he was Captain <hi>Germaine;</hi> he ſuppoſes if he ſaw him now he could know him.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes ſworn on behalf of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> for invalidating the Teſtimony of <hi>Thomas Lloyd.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALexander Herman</hi> ſaith, that he ſerved Mr. <hi>Germaine;</hi> he hath left his Service a year and a half, about eight Weeks after he came from <hi>Ireland</hi> with the King; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſerved him a Year and half: Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> was in <hi>Ireland</hi> with the King, in the Summer, in the Year 1690. He went to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> two days before the King that Summer, he continued there four Months: he believes he went the laſt of <hi>May,</hi> or the firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>June;</hi> he came back with the King. He the Witneſs ſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him all that while in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſaw him every Hour an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> every Day, and never ſtirr'd from him; he came from <hi>Ireland</hi> in the ſame Ship with the Lord <hi>Villers,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Mancheſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and Mr. <hi>Felton;</hi> and he went to <hi>Ireland</hi> in the <hi>Monmouth</hi> Yard with the Envoys of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Mompavillon:</hi> He ſaith Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> was at <hi>Bruſſels May</hi> laſt, he ſaw him there, and ſpoke with him there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192144:10"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aw the Lord <hi>Villers</hi> and the Lord <hi>Lumley</hi> there with him; he lodged in the ſame Tavern there with him, for four Days, and ſaw him not after: He the Witneſs, coming then for <hi>England,</hi> left him there. He never knew him wear his own Hair; his own Hair is dark brown: He never knew him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear abroad without a Wigg; his Hair is about half a Finger long; he wore a fair Perriwigg. He ſaith he, the Witneſs, was quarter'd in a little Tent behind him in <hi>Ireland;</hi> he could not ſtir but he heard him; he ſaith that four weeks after he ſaw him in <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> he ſaw him walking in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anthony Moree</hi> ſaith, he was Barber to Mr. <hi>Germaine;</hi> the firſt time he ſhaved him was about five or ſix years ſince; his own Hair is brown; he ſhaved his head very often; he ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him before he went to <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſince he came home; he never ſaw his Hair long enough to cover his Ears; nor ſaw he him ever wear his own Hair, but a Perriwigg: he ſhaved him for a year and half before and ſince he went for <hi>Ireland;</hi> he ſhaved him always at his own houſe near the Park: he or his man ſhaved him ever ſince he came from <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to this day: he or his man ſhaved him the night before the King went for <hi>Holland:</hi> he ſaith that Mr. <hi>Germaine;</hi> when he went away, ſaid it would be a Month or two before he ſhould come back, but he knows not how long it was: This was at his Houſe next door to the Cock-pit; he ſhaved him general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince the King came into <hi>England.</hi> he ſaith the Campaign was almoſt done when he firſt ſhaved him, after he came from <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LLoyd</hi>'s Depoſition is nothing at all to the purpoſe, or if it were never ſo pertinent, the Falſities in it are ſufficient to ſpoil it; for in truth his Evidence, as to Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s being at <hi>Fox Hall,</hi> is only grounded upon Hear-ſay and Report: And yet he ventures to ſwear him to be there every Month in both the laſt Summers; and particularly, that he was ſeveral times there in <hi>May, June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1690. Whereas <hi>Alexander Herman</hi> ſwears, that Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> went to <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Summer 1690, on the laſt of <hi>May,</hi> or on the firſt of <hi>June,</hi> where he ſtay'd about four Months, and that himſelf ſaw and ſerv'd him there; and ſays farther, that he was at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> in <hi>May</hi> laſt. <hi>Anthony Moree</hi> ſays alſo, being Barber to Mr. <hi>Germaine,</hi> that he went beyond Seas, and the Campaign was almoſt over when he firſt ſhaved him after he came back from <hi>Flanders,</hi> which is a flat Contradiction to <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
               <head>
                  <hi>The next Witneſſes produced by the Duke of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>were</hi> Peter Scriber, Andrew Anderſon, Robert Hemming, John Reynolds, <hi>and</hi> Margaret Foſter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter Scriber</hi> ſaith that he let an Houſe, at <hi>Fox Hall,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Daniel Germaine,</hi> Mid-Summer was two years, <hi>(viz)</hi> 1689, at Twenty four Pound <hi>per Annum.</hi> He told him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo Ladies that were to come from <hi>Holland</hi> were to live there; one was Mrs. <hi>Bryan,</hi> the other the Lady <hi>Bateman;</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent by the Name of <hi>Daniel Germaine</hi>'s and Captain <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Siſters. The Ladies came to the Houſe about ten days after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was let; one <hi>Goodman,</hi> that attended them, was off and on there all the time that the Lady <hi>Bateman</hi> lived there, which was off and on till <hi>September</hi> laſt. This <hi>Goodman</hi> is the ſame Man that was heard here the other day, as <hi>Henry Keymer</hi> he remembers nor, nor can be poſitive that he hath ſeen Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Germaine</hi> there at any time, he cannot ſay he knows him; he hath not ſeen him in ſeven or eight years. He ſaith, he, the Witneſs, is generally abſent in the Day-time; <hi>Goodman</hi> he ſaith came off and on to the Lady <hi>Bateman</hi>'s from the time ſhe came thither till the time ſhe went away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andrew Anderſon</hi> ſaith, he knew one that went by the Name of the Lady <hi>Bateman</hi> a year and half ago, at <hi>Fox-Hall,</hi> from laſt Spring was Twelve-months till near laſt <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> but hath not ſeen her ſince; he knew one that went by the Name of <hi>Goodman</hi> that uſed the Houſe; and that <hi>Goodman</hi> is <hi>Keymer;</hi> he knew a Geatleman that lived by the <hi>Cock-pit,</hi> that went by the Name of my Lady <hi>Bateman</hi>'s Brother, which he uſed to take into his Boat at <hi>Channel-Row,</hi> and carry to Mr. <hi>Scriber</hi>'s Houſe at <hi>Fox-hall.</hi> He carried him ſeveral times back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and forwards; ſince mid-ſummer he hath carr ed him twice; he uſed to carry him to the back Stairs of <hi>Scriber</hi>'s Houſe: The ſame day he fetched him, in the Forenoon, from the Parliament-Stairs, or <hi>Channel-Row,</hi> he carried him back in the Afternoon; he had a light Wigg. He, the Witneſs, hath carried Wood from <hi>Scriber</hi>'s Houſe, from the Perſon that went by the Name of the Lady <hi>Bateman,</hi> to the Houſe by the <hi>Cock-Pit;</hi> one <hi>Nicola</hi> uſed to receive it into Carts, at the <hi>Wool-Stable:</hi> This <hi>Nicola</hi> was, he ſuppoſes, Servant to the Gentleman that lives in that Houſe on the other ſide the <hi>Cock Pit;</hi> he hath been at the Door but never in the Houſe; he ſaith he bought the Wood of the Bargemen, by the Perſons Order that was called the Lady <hi>Bateman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Hemming</hi> ſaith, he knew one that lived near the Dye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in <hi>Fox-hall,</hi> that went by the Name of Lady <hi>Bateman;</hi> he ſaith, he was Gardner to the Houſe near two Years ſince, after <hi>Midſummer</hi> next will be three Years; he knows not the Lady otherwiſe than by the name of Lady <hi>Bateman;</hi> he hath ſeen Gentlemen come there, but he knows not their Names; he knew her Servant <hi>Goodman;</hi> Mr <hi>Knolles,</hi> that waited on the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and was chief Gardner, paid him his wages; he knew <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> by no other Name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Reynolds</hi> ſaith, that he ſaw the Lady that went by the name of Madam <hi>Bateman</hi> ſeveral times walking in her Garden, living conceal'd; that is, ſhe lived privately, and had but little Converſation amongſt her Neighbors. The ſixth of <hi>November</hi> laſt, being invited to dine at a Friends at <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> he met between the Lord <hi>Peterborough</hi>'s and the Ferry, a Lady whom he believed was the ſame Lady <hi>Bateman;</hi> and becauſe he would not be under a miſtake, he enquir'd of one that followed her, and he told him, it was the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> his buſineſs is at the next door to <hi>Scriber</hi>'s houſe; he hath ſeen a Gentleman walk with the Lady in the Garden, that his, the Witneſſes Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants have told him, was Mr. <hi>Germaine,</hi> he hath known the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy live in that place above two Years and half. He knew <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that lived there, who now goes by the Name of <hi>Keymer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Margaret Foſter</hi> ſaith, ſhe knows one <hi>Nichola,</hi> he's Mr. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi>'s Gentleman, that lives next houſe to the <hi>Cock-pit.</hi> Mr <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> hath lived there two Years; her Husband was his Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; it's the <hi>Royal Cock pit</hi> in <hi>Park-ſtreet,</hi> or <hi>Cartret-street;</hi> Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> ſent for her on <hi>Sunday</hi> Fortnight, to enquire for her Husband, who, he told her, was a Witneſs againſt him; and his Brother (who was preſent) told her, that his Brother did not ſend for her to bribe her, but to tell her Husband he ſhould not forſwear himſelf, for there was a Pillory.</p>
               <div type="observations">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:192144:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Obſervations upon the Depoſitions of</hi> Peter Scriber, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Anderſon, Robert Hemming, John Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds, <hi>and</hi> Margaret Foſter.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Teſtimonies are all Foreign to the Charge againſt the Dutcheſs; her Graces being at <hi>Fox-hall,</hi> and the going under borrowed Names, is all acknowledged, and the Reaſons already given; beſides the miſtakes in them are ſo few and trivial, that it is not worth the while to detect them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>
                  <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> Examined on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Dutcheſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAne Wadſworth</hi> ſaith, that ſhe ſold drink, and going into Mr. <hi>Germane</hi>'s Houſe, a little before the King went into <hi>Ireland,</hi> for a Pint Pot, ſhe ſaw a <hi>Dutch</hi> Woman, who bid her go up Stairs for it; and going up for it, ſhe met the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> in a Night-Gown, one ſide lapt over the other ſide-with <hi>Flanders</hi>-lac'd Night-Cloaths on her Head, without a Hood on: About two Hours after, <hi>Herman,</hi> Footman to <hi>Germaine,</hi> came into her Houſe and ſhe ſaying to him, you have got the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> at your Houſe, he ſaid, no Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk:</hi> I ſaid it was ſhe, for I had ſeen her ſome Hundreds of times: He ſaid, it was his Maſter's Lady, and his Maſter's Dutcheſs, no Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> why ſhould not my Maſter have a Dutcheſs as well at the Duke of <hi>Norfolk?</hi> She hath known Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> three Years next <hi>Midſummer,</hi> having lived there ſo long. <hi>Herman</hi> enquiring where I ſaw her, I ſaid upon the Stairs: he told me, I ſhould not have gone up the Stairs; I told him, the <hi>Dutch</hi>-Woman bid me go up, It was about Eleven a Clock in the day time that ſhe ſaw her: He bid me ſay no more of it, for if his Maſter knew it, he would kill the <hi>Dutch</hi>-woman. She ſaw Welſh <hi>Frank,</hi> about two Months ſince, deliver a Letter to Mr. <hi>Germaine,</hi> and ſhe hath ſeen her go to the Houſe often; ſhe hath known the Dutcheſs ever ſince, and before ſhe was married.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frances Knight</hi> (examined before for the Dutcheſs) being called in, the Witneſs ſaith, this is the Woman that was called <hi>Welſh Frank,</hi> whom ſhe hath often ſeen at Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s; ſhe ſaw her, about the time the King came home from <hi>Flanders,</hi> give another Letter to Mr. <hi>Nicola,</hi> Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Gentleman.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes produced by the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> to ſpeak to the Credit of <hi>Jane Wadſworth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JOhn Prince</hi> ſaith, he hath known <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> Twelve Years, to be a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d honeſt poor Woman, and of good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to the beſt of his Knowledge; and that ſhe takes care to maintain her Family; he believes her to be an honeſt Woman, and that ſhe would not take a falſe Oath; he knew her at the <hi>Horſe-ferry,</hi> and in <hi>Cartret-ſtreet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Emery Arguies</hi> ſaith, that he hath known <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> 13 or 14 years, he never knew her but of as good Reputation as any in the Pariſh; ſhe is Poor, but he believes, ſhe would not take a falſe Oath.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Robert Elmes</hi> ſaith, that he hath known <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> 12 or 13 years, he thinks her a very honeſt Woman, he never heard but ſhe was an honeſt Poor Woman, that endeavoured to live, and maintain her Family, ſhe is of good Reputation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Charles Read</hi> ſaith, he hath known <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> 12 years and ſomething better, he never knew her do an ill thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was always a careful induſtrious Woman; he hath known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> married all that time, and ſhe never was a Servant in the time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry Dagley</hi> Senior ſaith, that he hath known <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> 16 or 17 years, ſhe was always a very Civil Woman, and he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard other by her.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes Sworn on the behalf of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>folk,</hi> to the Invalidating the Teſtimony of <hi>Jane Wad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> worth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GRace Cooke</hi> ſaith, that ſhe knows <hi>Jane Wadſworth,</hi> ſhe hath lived near her Four Years; ſhe came into the Witneſſe Houſe with a Paper in her Hand, and asked her, who let it, ſaying, ſhe knew no hing of it; ſhe ſaid, that ſhe had ſaid that ſhe had ſeen the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> in Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Houſe, but ſhe had not ſeen her a great while, and now that ſhe had ſeen her, ſhe was ſatisfied, that it was not her; and ſhe wiſhed, that ſhe might burn in the Fire, and never go hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to her Children, if ſhe would take her Oath of it. The Pape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was to warn her to this Houſe; it was the firſt Night the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers came out, that ſhe ſaid this, <hi>Hoſea Grimſly, John Hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Margaret Coudy</hi> were preſent when ſhe ſaid this; ſhe ſaith, ſhe lives next Door but one to <hi>Jane Wadſworth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Hall</hi> ſaith, that he hath known <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> above a year; about a Fort-night ſince ſhe came into Mrs. <hi>Gook</hi>'s, with an Order in her hand, but knew not who left it; and ſaid, ſhe could ſay nothing to it, Mrs. <hi>Cooke</hi> ſaying again, you muſt ſay ſomething to it, elſe you had not had this Order from the Houſe; then ſhe ſaid, ſhe had been at the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s and had told the Duke, that ſhe chanced to go into Captain <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Houſe for a Pint Pot, and ſhe chanced to ſee the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> but ſhe ſaid ſhe might be miſtaken, for ſhe had not ſeen her in ſeven years before, but ſhe had ſeen her once or twice ſince ſhe came out of <hi>France,</hi> and that was none of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> which ſhe ſaw on Captain <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Stairs; whereupon <hi>Hoſea Grimſly</hi> asking her, if ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were ſure is was not ſhe, ſhe ſaid, ſhe was ſure it was not ſhe wiſhing that ſhe might burn, and never go home to he Children, if ſhe would ſwear it, for ſhe could not ſwear it <hi>Hoſea Grimſly, Grace Cook,</hi> and two other Women, were preſent in <hi>Grace Cook</hi>'s Houſe, when this diſcourſe happened, which was the very Night the Order came out: He ſaith, he wrough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Houſe, he ſaw twice or thrice Ladies ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Masks; one of the Ladies in the Mask, gave Order to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> down a Partition; ſhe was reported to be Captain <hi>Germaine</hi> Siſter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Margaret Coudy</hi> ſaith, ſhe knows <hi>Jane Wadſworth,</hi> who cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into Mrs. <hi>Cook</hi>'s the firſt time ſhe was ſubpoena'd, and asked who left the Paper in her Hand for her; ſhe ſaid, ſhe we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s for a Pot, and ſhe thought ſhe ſaw the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> there; but ſhe ſaw her ſince her coming fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>France,</hi> and was ſatisfied it was not her, and wiſhed ſhe mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> never ſee her Children, and burn, if ever ſhe ſaw her there.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander Herman</hi> ſaith, that he knows <hi>Jane [Wadſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> well, he never had any Diſcourſe with her concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolks</hi> being in Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi>'s Houſe; he ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he hath drank often at <hi>Wadſworth</hi>'s Houſe, but he never ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Diſcourſe with her concerning the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192144:11"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:192144:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192144:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:192144:13"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192144:13"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> this Woman in his Maſters Houſe in all his life: He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> his Maſter at Table, and in his Chamber, all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of his Service, which was a Year and half; he never ſaw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dy in a Mask in his Maſters Houſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> ſaith, that ſhe knows <hi>Jane Wadſworth,</hi> ſhe was her Servant, but not long, for ſhe was not honeſt. She, the Witneſs, being gone out, at her return, ſhe met her going away with her, the Witneſs's Linnen and her Husbands, bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled up; this is about Eleven Years ſince.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Frances Knight</hi> ſaith, that ſhe knows not <hi>Jane Wadſworth,</hi> nor never diſcourſed with her, nor never ſaw her at <hi>Mr. Germaine</hi>'s Houſe, nor did the Witneſs ever carry any Letters thither.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Witneſſes examined on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> againſt the Credit of <hi>John Hall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEnry Dagley,</hi> Jun. ſaith, that he knows <hi>John Hall,</hi> he was a Workman at <hi>Mr. Germaine</hi>'s, when he, the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wrought there; and <hi>Hall</hi> hath often ſaid to him, that he believed it was the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> that was there in the mask, and that gave him Directions in his Work there; this was at <hi>Mr. Germaine</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Park-ſtreet:</hi> He could not affirm it to be true, becauſe ſhe was masked, but really believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Hoskins</hi> ſaith, that <hi>John Hall</hi> was employed by <hi>Mr. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> and a Lady that was masked; the Lady was the firſt that ever ſhewed him his work, what he was to do: And the firſt work he did was to take do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> talking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, that it was the Dutc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>John Hall</hi> has ſaid that that Lady was the Dutcheſs of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> not that he could ſay ſo of his own Knowledge, but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ath been often told it was ſo; he ſaith that <hi>Hall</hi> told him, the day he, the ſaid <hi>Hall,</hi> was examined here, that if he had been ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more he could have ſaid more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <head>Obſervations upon the foregoing Evidence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JAne Wadſworth</hi> ſwears, ſhe ſaw the Dutcheſs at Mr. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi>'s, and what Diſcourſe ſhe had afterward with <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Mr. Germaine</hi>'s Footman, and that a Dutch-woman ſent her up Stairs for a Pint Pot, by which Accident ſhe ſaw the Dutcheſs; ſhe ſays alſo, that ſhe ſaw Welſh <hi>Frank</hi> deliver a Letter to <hi>Mr. Germaine; Frances Knight</hi> being produc'd <hi>Wadſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> ſwears that's the Woman that was called Welſh <hi>Frank,</hi> and that ſhe ſaw her give another Letter once to <hi>Mr. Nichola, Mr. Germaines</hi> Gentleman; there are alſo four Witneſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for her Credit, that ſay they know no Ill by her.</p>
                  <p>But then <hi>Grace Cook</hi> on the other hand ſwears, that <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> told her, that ſhe thought ſhe had ſeen the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs at <hi>Mr. Germaines,</hi> but was now ſatisfied that it was not ſhe, and curſed her ſelf, and her Children, if ſhe would take her Oath that it was the Dutches: This was upon her receiving a <hi>Subpoena,</hi> to appear and give Evidence; <hi>Hoſea Grimſley, John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>all</hi> and <hi>Margaret Condy</hi> were preſent at this diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Hall</hi> ſwears, that ſhe ſaid that ſhe ſaw the Dutcheſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Norfolk</hi> at Captain <hi>Germaines,</hi> but upon a further ſight of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſhe finds ſhe was miſtaken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoſea Grimſly</hi> ſwears to the diſcourſe, the very words of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Curſe, and the Perſons that were in Company; all agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Depoſitions of <hi>Grace Cook: Margaret Condy</hi> ſwears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the very ſame Particulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander Herman</hi> depoſes, that he never ſaw <hi>Wadſwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> his Maſters Houſe, nor ever had any Diſcourſe with her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Dutcheſs; and he being a Perſon turned away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> diſgrace from his Maſter, would have made no ſcruple to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh any Secret of that kind, at leaſt to ſwear the truth wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> upon his Oath.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> ſays, that <hi>Jane Wadſworth</hi> was her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant a while, but was not honeſt, and that ſhe had filched ſome of hers and her Husbands Linnen, and was going away with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Frances Knight</hi> denies the Knowledge of <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> or any diſcourſe with her; ſhe never ſaw her at <hi>Mr. Germaines,</hi> nor ever carried any Letters thither.</p>
                  <p>But here are two Witneſſes brought in now to Arraign the Credit of <hi>John Hall,</hi> which is as much as to ſay that they had no Exceptions to any of the reſt, or, which is all one, to the truth of the matter; for <hi>John Halls</hi> Evidence is by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed over and over: And what is it that theſe two Witneſſes have to ſay at laſt? <hi>Henry Dagler</hi> ſays, that he believed it was the Dutcheſs he ſaw at <hi>Mr. Germaine</hi>'s, but could not affirm it. And <hi>John Hoskins</hi> ſays, that they ſaid it was the Dutcheſs, but he could not ſpeak it of his own Knowledge, which amounts to no more than a bare Hear-ſay.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
               <head>Witneſſes Sworn on the behalf of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> intimating a ſeeming Reconciliation.</head>
               <p>MRs. <hi>Judith Stourton</hi> ſaith, that ſhe was Servant to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> when the Report was of the Dutcheſs and <hi>Mr. Germaine,</hi> which was about a week before the Duke and Dutcheſs went to <hi>France;</hi> ſhe was askt by the Lord <hi>Peterborow</hi> in the preſence of the Duke of <hi>Norſolk,</hi> in the Dukes Houſe in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Square (where they ſhut the door) as ſhe would Anſwer it to the Face of Almighty God, if ſhe did know whether his daughter was an Adultreſs: Her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, that as ſhe hoped to ſee God in Heaven, the Dutcheſs was as Vertuous as any Woman alive, for ought ſhe knew; ſhe ſaith, that what ſhe then ſaid, is true; and if ſhe ſhould pretend to ſay more, ſhe ſhould wrong her: She ſaith, that no one was preſent beſides the Lord <hi>Peterborow</hi> and the Duke, when they examined her; and that ſhe ſaw no Shirt or Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat at that time; and that ſhe doth not remember, ſhe ſaid to <hi>Mrs. Webb</hi> any thing concerning the Dutcheſs and <hi>Mr. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> and thinks ſhe never ſpoke with <hi>Mrs. Webb;</hi> and ſhe was not at <hi>Windſor</hi> when the Duke was at <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> ſhe ſaith, there was a Report of Scandals which ſhe was ſorry for.</p>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Edith Sawbridge</hi> and <hi>Webb,</hi> produced on the behalf of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> to diſcredit the Teſtimony of Mrs. <hi>Stourton.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDith Sawbridge</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Tueſday</hi> following, this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Diſcourſe concerning the Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk; Mrs. Stourton</hi> came into her Chamber, and ſhe telling her what had happen'd at <hi>Windſor, Mrs. Stourton</hi> reply'd, this is nothing but what ſhe expected before now; the Witneſs reply'd, that if ſhe the Witneſs had been as near the Dutcheſs, as the ſaid <hi>Mrs. Stourton,</hi> ſhe would have prevented all this, to which Mrs.
<pb facs="tcp:192144:14"/>
                     <hi>Stourton</hi> anſwer'd would you have had me whipt at the Carts-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>. The diſcourſe we had was, that <hi>Mrs. Knifton</hi> told her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en I came from <hi>London</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> Night, that ſhe told me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e was glad I was come, for ſhe expected her Throat to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>very Night, ſince my Lord Duke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> went to <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> her the Reaſon of her fear, ſhe anſwered, <hi>Germaine</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with my Lady Dutcheſs, ever ſince my Lord Duke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nt to <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> that when he came home he would hear of it, and he would kick her for a Baud; and if ſhe ſhould tell my Lord, <hi>Germaine</hi> would cut her Throat; I bid her have a care what ſhe ſaid, for theſe were dangerous words; how can you prove this? ſhe ſaid, it was very true; the Witneſs asking her (Mrs. <hi>Knifton</hi>) how ſhe knew this? ſhe ſaid, <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> inſtead of going home, went into the Cloſet: The Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot ſay, that ſhe ſaid all this to <hi>Mrs. Stourton,</hi> but the greateſt part ſhe did ſay, <hi>Mrs. Stourton</hi> ſaid, this was nothing but what ſhe expected before: This was the <hi>Tueſday</hi> after my Lord Duke came from <hi>Portſmouth;</hi> this was about <hi>Bartholomew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide,</hi> in the firſt year of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="testimony_of_witnesses">
                  <head>Mrs. <hi>Stourton</hi> called in, to confront this <hi>Edith Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bride,</hi> and Examined.</head>
                  <p>MRs. <hi>Judith Stourton</hi> ſaith, that ſhe ſaw <hi>Mrs. Sawbridge</hi> once in the Dukes Houſe in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Square, and they talkt of the Slander of <hi>Germaine</hi> and the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Norfolk;</hi> ſhe ſaith, ſhe the Witneſs, never heard <hi>Mrs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>awbridge</hi> ſay, that <hi>Mrs. Knifton</hi> ſhould ſay, that <hi>Germaine</hi> lay with the Dutcheſs every night at <hi>Windſor;</hi> ſhe denies, that ſhe ſaid to <hi>Mrs. Sawbridge,</hi> that ſhe expected to hear that before now; ſhe never ſaid to Mrs. <hi>Sawbridge,</hi> Would you have me whipt at the Carts-arſe; ſhe ſaith, ſhe remembers not that <hi>Mrs. Sawbridge</hi> told her, that <hi>Mrs. Knifton</hi> ſaid, that ſhe was afraid that her Throat would have been cut, when the Duke was at <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> ſhe remembers not, that ſhe askt <hi>Mrs. Sawbridge</hi> the reaſon of <hi>Mrs. Kniftons</hi> fear, or that ſhe told her any thing of <hi>Mrs. Kniftons</hi> ſaying, that <hi>Germaine</hi> had lain with my Lady eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night at <hi>Windſor;</hi> ſhe ſaw <hi>Mrs. Sawbridge,</hi> and diſcourſed with her, but ſhe cannot ſay what diſcourſe ſhe had with her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mrs. Eliz. Camell</hi> ſaith, that ſhe went with the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Norfolk</hi> into <hi>France;</hi> they went together very loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and parted ſo; ſhe thinks the Duke ſtaid with her about a fortnight; the Dukes Eye was ill, and my Lady went often to him; and when ſhe did ſo, we retired; my Lady dreſt his Eye, they eat and drank together every day, they did not lodge together that ſhe knows; my Lord told her at parting at the Grate in the Monaſtery, that he would fetch her away ſuddenly, and they parted kindly; <hi>Mrs. Lawſon</hi> was in the Monaſtery with the Dutcheſs; the Witneſs continued there about ſeventeen months; my Lord expreſt a great deal of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to my Lady in going, and while he was there; there were Tears on both ſides at parting: When my Lord and Lady were together in the Houſe called <hi>L'Hotel de Terrau</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> we uſed to withdraw, not knowing what they had to ſay together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr. Matthew Scott</hi> ſaith, that he paid ſeveral Sums to the Dutcheſs, from the Duke; in <hi>May</hi> 1688. he paid 125 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> for the Dutcheſs, to <hi>Mr. Cragg;</hi> he paid 2 or 300 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> in <hi>France,</hi> when the Duke and Dutcheſs were there; he cannot ſay, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any money into <hi>France,</hi> after the Duke came home; he knows not that any money <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> paid to <hi>Mr.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by the Dukes Order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr. Robert Welborne</hi> ſaith, that about the middle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> laſt, the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſent for him by <hi>Mr. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> his Grace in his Room, by the Lords Houſe, which acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly he did; his Grace told him, there had been ſome me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and propoſals, by Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> but he lookt on them both to be men of great Buſineſs, and could not attend on ſuch Matters, and therefore he ſent for him, knowing him to be willing, to do any Services between them. The firſt thing his Grace deſired, was to acquaint his Wife, and the Lady <hi>Peterborow,</hi> and he thinks he Named the Lord <hi>Peterborow,</hi> that he expected to be Indemnified from the Dutcheſs's Equipage; for, ſays he, I hear ſhe is ſetting up for a great Equipage, and I deſire to be free from being obliged to pay for any of that; he told his Grace, that he thought he was miſinformed, for all the Equipage he ſaw, was a Coach, Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, two Foot-men, a pair of Horſes, and two or three more Servants; but, ſays his Grace, I formerly paid Money for her, to one <hi>Mourton,</hi> and ſhould be unwilling to do ſo again; I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume my Lord Duke, ſaid he, that was a Debt contracted, while your Grace and the Dutcheſs lived together; but ſays his Grace, pray do you acquaint them of it, for this is what I expect.</p>
                  <p>Next, ſays his Grace, my Wife has ſome pretenſions upon <hi>Caſtle-Riſing,</hi> which I could Sell without her Conſent, by loſing Two Thouſand, or Two Thouſand Five Hundred Pounds; and beſides, I find ſhe hath alſo a pretention upon <hi>Billing,</hi> which I never knew till very lately, when I was upon ſelling of that Reverſion; but, I ſhould have been an ill man, to pretend to do that if I had known of any ſuch Incumbrance. Therefore, I would have you tell my Wife, that if ſhe will conſent to the Sale of thoſe Eſtates, and make me eaſy in that particular; let her conſider, wherein I may make her eaſy, and I ſhall do it: I know ſhe was a great Lover of <hi>Drayton,</hi> and I ſuppoſe is ſo ſtill; and ſhe did once offer me a conſiderable Sum of Money for my Life in it; therefore let her conſider of this matter, and if ſhe can propoſe any thing for her eaſe and quiet, on theſe Terms, I ſhall comply with her.</p>
                  <p>I do not ſay to threaten her: But I am told, that for the Reaſon of there being either One and Twenty, or Two and Twenty <hi>Catholick</hi> Heirs of my Family before One <hi>Proteſtant</hi> One; if I would bring in a Bill of Divorce, I ſhould obtain it on that account; he told his Grace he ſhould be ſorry to hear of any ſuch thing: But in Obedience to his Grace's Commands, he would acquaint the Dutcheſs with it; accordingly he did, the ſame day, and Lady <hi>Peterborow</hi> both: her Grace was very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at the meſſage, eſpecially at that part that mentioned a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce; and he was ſent the next morning to Mr. <hi>Scott,</hi> to deſire him to acquaint the Duke, that as he was my Lord <hi>Peterborow</hi>'s Servant, it was not fit for him to receive nor bring ſuch meſſages. But if his Grace had any thing to ſay, it was moſt proper, by a Servant of his own, or to ſend for one of hers. I carried the meſſage the next morning to <hi>Mr. Scott,</hi> and at my return home, the Dutcheſs ſhewed me a Letter ſhe had Writ to the Duke, to the ſame purpoſe, and which was ſent to his Grace, but not by him; the Dutcheſs did declare, when he propoſed the Sale of <hi>Caſtle-Riſing</hi> and <hi>Billing,</hi> as the Duke had deſired, that ſhe would never Conſent to it. By any of this Diſcourſe it di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not appear to him, that the Duke ſhowed any Inclinations to live with the Dutcheſs, nor did he underſtand it ſo.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="summation">
               <pb facs="tcp:192144:14"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Judith Stour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sawbridge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>beth Camell, <hi>Mr.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thew Scott, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Robert Welborne.</head>
               <p>THE Reader will find this Diſcourſe about Mr. <hi>Germaine</hi> and the Dutcheſs, to be a Scandal of a matter of, Six <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ears ſtanding; <hi>Hudſon,</hi> a Caſt Footman, has ſworn to the Shirt and Waſtcoat, and that he immediately told my Lord of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>Ann Burton</hi> ſwears likewiſe (with another falſe Oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween her Teeth) that this Shirt and Waſtecoat were ſent by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Duke to the Lord <hi>Peterborows.</hi> It follows now to be noted, what courſe has been taken from the Firſt to the Laſt, for a thorough Diſcovering of the Truth of this matter, and how it comes to paſs that the Thunder-bolt ſhould hang in the Air, ſo many Years, after the Breaking of the Cloud.</p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Stourton</hi> is here upon her double Oath, firſt under the Shrift of the Duke and my Lord <hi>Peterborow,</hi> who took her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately and Adjured her, as ever ſhe hoped to ſee God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to declare what ſhe knew as to the Dutcheſs being an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, ſhe purg'd her ſelf upon her hopes of Salvation, that the Dutcheſs was as Vertuous as any Woman alive for ought ſhe knew; ſhe ſwore the ſame thing over again at the Bar of the Houſe of Lords; and being Interrogated about the Shirt and Waſtcoat before ſpoken of, ſhe ſwore likewiſe, that ſhe ſaw no Shirt or Waſtcoat at that time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edith Sawbridge</hi> was now produc'd againſt the Credit of Mrs. <hi>Judith Stourton,</hi> and lays the ſtreſs of her Evidence upon what Mrs. <hi>Knifton</hi> ſaid, which has been the very Pinch of the Queſtion throughout the whole Cauſe, and the Proſecution has ſtill been at a Fault when it came to any material Point; that is to ſay, only the Hear-ſay Witneſſes are produced, and thoſe that can ſpeak upon knowledge, and poſitively to the Fact, are withdrawn, or conceal'd, contrary to the Practice and Reaſon of all Judicial Proceedings.</p>
               <p>Mrs. <hi>Stourton</hi> is called in again to confront <hi>Edith Sawbridge,</hi> and denies every Article in her Depoſition, one by one, that is of any moment; but at the ſame time there appears no Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on the other hand, to the Credit of Mrs. <hi>Stourton:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be imagined, that any woman ſhould dare to ſwear falſe, in a Caſe where two ſuch Witneſſes ſhould be privy to the Perjury.</p>
               <p>It follows now to be noted, what Courſe has been taken for a thorough Diſcovery of this Intrigue, according to the uſual Methods of Honour and Juſtice. The Examination of Mrs. <hi>Stourton</hi> by the Duke and my Lord <hi>Peterborow,</hi> was as ſolemn, ſtrict and private as the Caſe requir'd; and it was while the Clamour was freſh too: So that there was no time loſt when they entered upon the Scrutiny. It will be ſeen in that which follows, by what degrees the Heat of this Calumny cooled, and what brought it on again.</p>
               <p>The Duke and Dutcheſs went for <hi>France</hi> together, about a Week after the Breaking out of this Clamour, and <hi>Elizabeth Camel</hi> waited upon the Dutcheſs; who ſwears, that they went lovingly together, and parted with Tears on both ſides; my Lord telling her Grace at Parting, that he would fetch her away ſuddenly. They eat and drunk together every Day, and were frequently together in private; but ſhe cannot ſay they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odg'd together. So that thus far, in all outward Appearance, the Miſunderſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed in ſome meaſure to be com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> ſpeaks only to the matter of Monies, and Accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which is little or nothing to the purpoſe in this place, except on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to the One Hundred Twenty and Five Pounds, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to be paid by him, for the Dutcheſs's uſe; which was a Quarterly Payment out of Five Hundred Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged and ordered by the High-Commiſſion Court to be paid to her, in lieu of Almony.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Robert Welborne</hi> comes to the very Merits of the Cauſe, and the preſent State of the Queſtion. He depoſes, that in <hi>November</hi> laſt the Duke ſent for him, and told him (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things by the by) that the Dutcheſs had ſome Pretenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon <hi>Caſtle-Riſing,</hi> and alſo upon <hi>Billing;</hi> and thereupon order'd the Witneſs to give her Grace to underſtand, that if ſhe would conſent to the Sale of thoſe Eſtates, and make the Duke eaſie in that particular, let her but conſider wherein he himſelf might make the Dutcheſs eaſie too, and upon thoſe Terms he would do it.</p>
               <p>His Grace told the Witneſs farther, that here being One or Two and Twenty Catholick Heirs to the Family, before one Proteſtant Heir, if (ſays his Grace) I would bring a Bill of Divorce, (I do not ſay it to threaten her) I could obtain it on that Account. The Witneſs acquainted both the Dutcheſs and the Lady <hi>Peterborow,</hi> the very ſame day with the ſubſtance of this meſſage, her Grace taking it very heinouſly to be told of a divorce; and the next day the Dutcheſs ſhewed the Witneſs a Letter ſhe wrote to the Duke upon this Occaſion; declaring, that for <hi>Castle-Riſing</hi> and <hi>Billing,</hi> ſhe would never part with them.</p>
               <p>It appears from hence, that upon the Examination of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs. <hi>Stourton,</hi> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her neceſſary Enquiries into the ground of this Scandal, the violence of the firſt Impreſſion was ſo far taken off, that according to the Evidence of <hi>Elizabeth Camel,</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord was pleaſed to treat the Dutcheſs with all Inſtances of Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Reſpect, both upon their paſſage into <hi>France,</hi> and upon the Places there, thoſe of the Bed only excepted. In this ſtate matters have continued ſome five or ſix Years now, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hout any Speech or Thought of a Divorce, that ever the Dutcheſs heard of till Mid-<hi>November</hi> laſt, in a meſſage by Mr. <hi>Wellborne</hi> from the Duke, and that was but upon a certain condition nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, however it was improved afterwards into a Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſeventh of <hi>January</hi> following was formally brought into the Lords Houſe.</p>
               <p>The Reader will need no other Light to a true underſtanding of the ſtrait her Grace was in, upon this Surprize, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages ſhe was expoſed to, than what he has here before him, in the Order of the Journal it ſelf: Where he will find the Dutcheſs ſo ſcanted for time to produce Witneſſes, and prepare her defence, that it was a wonderful Pro idence ſhe ſhould do ſo much as ſhe did. Though in the mean while, her Grace has loſt the benefit of ſeveral conſiderable Witneſſes, for want of time to find them out, and bring them together. Now as for Mr. <hi>Wellborne</hi>'s Depoſition, it carries the Countenance rather of a Treaty than an Accuſation; the Duke's part is only a calm de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate diſcourſe, conſulting the Reciprocal Eaſe both of himſelf and of the Dutcheſs. Terms are propoſed and promiſed, and not one Word or Glance of Reproach from one end to the other of it. Mr. <hi>Welborne</hi> (upon the Duke's asking him, at the Lords Bar, if by his diſcourſe he underſtood an Inclination to live with the Dutcheſs) 'tis true, did not gather from his words, as if he had any thought of living with her; the only hard thing ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192144:15"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> about his Catholick Heirs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich ſeem'd to turn the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of Adultery into a Caſe of Religion. Let any Creature judge now, whether the Dutcheſs durſt to have ſtood it out thus, if ſhe had been guilty of ſo foul a Crime, when ſhe might have been ſafe and free, as appears by the Propoſal, upon Terms ſo much more eaſy.</p>
               <p>To make a ſhort Summary now of the Whole, a Word firſt to the Character and Quality of the Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>There is <hi>Owen,</hi> a Street-Porter, brought in as a Witneſs to the Privacies of the Dutcheſs's Bed-Chamber, beſides ſeveral un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable Exceptions to the Particulars of his Evidence. There is <hi>Ellwood,</hi> a Cobler's Wife, and a Jilting little Slut, that's as palpably detected of Falſity, as the other. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> a poor Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guy, Tricking Footman, that was turned off for his ill Bahavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. <hi>Burton,</hi> a beggerly Wench, that cheated her Landlady, and forſwore her ſelf in this Cauſe at the Lords Bar: <hi>Varelst,</hi> a Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and by Intervals, a Madman: <hi>Foſter,</hi> a Coachman that was turn'd off by his Maſter, and ſwore to be reveng'd of him. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> under ſeveral manifeſt miſtakes, but nothing to the main Cauſe. <hi>Scriber, Anderſon, Hemming, Reynolds,</hi> and <hi>Margaret Foſter,</hi> ſay not one word to the purpoſe: <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> a pilfering Servant, that robb'd her Miſtreſs, and her Evidence moſt notoriouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd.</p>
               <p>Now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of their own Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ny'd to have a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> very extraordinary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their Depoſition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Proſecutors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſecond the ſwear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>idence: Tho' it is ſufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they could have ſound them if they would have ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cauſe upon that ſtreſs. It is to be conſidered once m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a difference there has been, betwixt the demeanour of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſide and the other, towards the Evidence. What Promi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and engaging Obligations on the one hand, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as one word or deed, directly or indirectly, that looked like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice or Prepoſſeſſion on the other part of the Dutcheſ.</p>
               <p>Let this be taken in the ſofteſt ſenſe, for it is a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, when officious Inſtruments that, are foreward to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Scandals, meet with eaſie and good natur'd Diſpoſition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that are too open perhaps to receive them. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ſame meaſure, to remove the prejudice of thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> willfully Deaf and Blind; and for the reſt, it is left to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Providence to bring the Truth to light in its du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and to vindicate the Cauſe of the Innocent and Oppreſſed.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_face_powder">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THat famous <hi>Powder,</hi> called <hi>Arcanum Magnum,</hi> formerly prepared by the Learned <hi>Riverius,</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſician Regent to the <hi>French</hi> King, and approved by moſt Perſons of Quality in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerving and beautifying the <hi>Face;</hi> it takes away all Heat Pimples, Sun-burnt, and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phew. In ſhort, it adds more <hi>Luſtre</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> than any <hi>Powder</hi> or Waſh known, as many Perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Quality can teſtifie, who daily uſe it with the greateſt Approbation; it is prepared only by <hi>J. H.</hi> Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in Phyſick, in <hi>Great Knight Riders-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Doctors Commons gate,</hi> a <hi>Blew Ball</hi> being over the Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where it may be had for 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> the Paper, with Directions for the Uſe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
